yes, that's the problem
對,這是那個問題
OK
OK
because it can get from us to here
因為這可以從我們到這邊
that we just said
那剛才我們說
but we can't see
可是我們看不出來
Can
可以
OK, OK
可以,OK
OK
OK
You've been therefore, so long, you have been standing in your송.
You've been therefore, so long, you have been standing in your송.
Please put your phone on silent to remind you that this presentation is in progress
請將手機調為靜音提醒您本演講進行中
Wear a mask all the way and prohibit eating and drinking videos and audio recordings
進行全程配戴口罩並禁止飲食錄影及錄音
Do not use the flash when taking pictures
拍照時請勿使用閃光燈
Thank you for your cooperation
感謝您的配合
Also in order to make our event better
另外為了使我們的活動更好
Need your valuable opinion
需要您的寶貴意見
Please use the wireless network at the venue
請可利用會場的無線網路
please stop here
請在此為止
Scan event QR code
掃描活動QR code
Help us fill out the online questionnaire
幫我們填達線上文卷後
After confirming the completed screen to the off-site service desk staff
將完成畫面給場外服務台工作人員確認後
You can get a beautiful small etiquette
即可獲得精美小禮儀份
Thanks
謝謝
110 years of Academia Sinica
中央研究院110年
111 Years of Knowledge Feast
111年知識饗宴
Dean Zhu Jiahua
朱家華院長
Science Lecture Begins
科普講座開始
Vice President Zhou Meiyin is invited to host
請周美寅副院長為主持
Academician Li, distinguished guests and colleagues, good night everyone
李院士 各位來賓 各位同仁 大家晚安
Welcome everyone to join our knowledge feast today
歡迎大家今天來參加我們的知識饗宴
Dean Zhu Jiahua's popular science lecture
朱家華院長柯普講座
This year is Zhu Jiahua Gu's 130-year-old list
今年是朱家華顧院長的130歲的名單
Every year we hold commemorative Cope Lectures
每年我們都會舉行紀念的柯普演講
express our condolences and respect
表達我們的追思和敬意
When Dean Zhu signed the table in this hospital
朱院長在本院簽臺的時候
In a situation of considerable shortage of resources and funds
資源經費相當短缺的狀況下
Establishment of a new residence in Nangang
在南港建立新的院舍
Then rebuilt the Institute of Plants, Institute of Chemistry and Institute of Zoology
然後重建了植物所 化學所 動物所
Jingshi Institute and Democracy Institute were also built
也興建了靜石所與民主所
For the development of the college's wishes and academics
為本院的願務發展及學術人士
Talent cultivation has laid a solid foundation
才培育奠定了堅實的基礎
So today our lecture
所以今天我們的講座
Special invitation to National Tsing Hua University
特別邀請到國立清華大學
Li Dingguo Distinguished Research Chair Professor, Department of Physics
物理系李定國特聘研究講座教授
He is an academician of the Mathematics Group of our college
他是本院數理組的院士
come and speak for us
來為我們演講
Academician Li is a Bachelor of Physics from National Taiwan University
李院士是臺灣大學的物理學士
Ph.D., Department of Physics, Brown University, USA
美國布朗大學物理系博士
at CUNY and UC
在紐約市立大學跟加州大學分校
postdoctoral research
擔任博士後研究
He was from 1982 to 1996
他在1982年到1996年
Taught in the Department of Physics, Virginia Polytechnic University
任教於維吉尼亞州立理工大學物理系
America against China in 1996
1996年之美反國
Institute of Physics
任職於本院的物理所
Also from 2012 to 2018
也在2012年到2018年
Acting as the director of the Institute of Physics
擔任本院物理所所長
Academician Li is a
李院士是一名
a well-known physicist
一個知名的物理學家
Lin Yushi in Ningtai theoretical many-body physics
林玉師在寧泰理論多體物理
His greatest contribution was to propose the theory
他最大的貢獻是提出了理論
Explain the special physical phenomenon of high temperature superbody
解釋高溫超體的特別的物理現象
It is all caused by the strong optical connection of electrons.
都是電子的強光連性造成的
So today he will introduce us to
所以今天他等於會為我們介紹一下
This group behavior in this heart camp
在這個心營的這種群體行為
he got many awards
他得到了很多的獎項
Contains the 2003 National Science Council Distinguished Research Award
包含了2003年國科會的傑出研究獎
2005 Hou Jindui Distinguished Honor Award
2005年侯金堆的傑出榮譽獎
With the 2019 Special Contribution Award of the Taiwan Physical Society
跟2019年臺灣物理學會的特殊貢獻獎
He is a Fellow of the American and British Physical Societies
他是美國及英國物理學會的會士
Elected as a Fellow of the Academy in 2018
在2018年當選為本院的院士
During service in Taiwan
在臺灣的服務期間
He was from 2004 to 2006
他是在2004年到2006年
In charge of the Nano-National Technology Project
擔任奈米國家型科技計畫的
kind of subject
種主詞人
Promoted from basic science to industrial application
推動了從基礎科學到產業應用
Core Facility Sharing
設立了核心設施共享
Various development plans to talent cultivation
到人才培育的各項發展計畫
so today we are very happy
所以今天我們非常高興
Academician Li
邀請到李院士
For us from the title of this speech is
為我們從這個演講的題目是
From quantum to classical physics
從量子到古典物理中
limited group behavior
有限的心引群體行為
this is what we are looking forward to
這是我們非常期待
with this brilliant speech
有這個精采的演講
So we now welcome Academician Li with applause
所以我們現在以掌聲歡迎李院士
we are
我們是
Thank you Vice President Zhou for the invitation
謝謝周副院長的邀請
His introduction is greatly appreciated
他的介紹非常感激
Vice President Zhou can invite me to come today
周副院長能夠請我來今天
This is the list of all Dean Zhu Jiahua
這朱家華全院長的名單
To have this opportunity to remember him with him
能有這個機會跟他來緬懷他一下
In fact, the reason why I am very happy is that
那其實我特別高興的原因是另外
In addition to my Academia Sinica for more than 20 years
除了我的中研院做了二十幾年
It was Master Chang Ang's bribery and Dean Zhu Quan's
是長昂師的受賄與朱全院長的
outside of help
幫助以外
sorry
對不起
Apart from the help of Dean Zhu Quan
朱全院長的幫助以外
Besides, I actually have some other connection with him.
另外我其實跟他還有一些別的關聯性
This correlation is the physical problem I want to talk about today
這個關聯性是我今天起了要談的物理問題
Then this correlation is that Dean Zhu Jiahua’s nerve is Sun Yat-sen University
那這個關聯性是朱家華院長神經是中山大學
Di Zixi, this is not Sun Yat-sen University in Kaohsiung
弟子溪那這不是高雄的中山大學
Sun Yat-sen University in Guangzhou
是在廣州的中山大學
Of course, his disciple Xi Xi is called the play director and vice principal.
他當然弟子溪叫做戲主任副校長
Headmaster for many years
校長 很多年
why did i mention this in particular
為什麼我特別提到這一點呢
Because my father-in-law, Principal Zhou Fengqi
因為我的岳父 周峰奇校長
Also graduated from Sun Yat-Sen University
也是中山大學畢業的
Actually he
其實他
My father-in-law and his family are in business in Guiyang
我的岳父他們家裡是從商的 在貴陽
His reasons for doing education
他的原因做從事教育的原因
In fact, it was inspired by Dean Zhu
其實是受了朱院長的啟發
Dean Zhu especially encouraged him to engage in education
朱院長特別鼓勵他要從事教育
So he held it in Guiyang and started to organize
所以他在貴陽就舉辦了開始辦
When I was in middle school for a while, I was fighting
暫時中學那時候在打仗的時候
run a temporary middle school
辦暫時中學
In fact, a lot of money
其實很多的經費
It was run with money from their own family business.
是從他們自己家裡經商拿錢出來辦的
This is what I think his whole life
這個是我覺得他這一輩子
are contributing to education
都是在貢獻教育
student development
學生的培育
I think it is worthy of my admiration
我覺得是很值得我欽佩的
I personally appreciate this of course
我個人當然感謝這個
Dean Zhu's contribution to this education
朱院長對這個教育的貢獻
There is a very big effort to contribute to Taiwan's education
對台灣教育的貢獻有非常大的努力
I have many classmates now
我現在有很多同學
In fact, it was Chiayi Middle School back then.
其實當年也都是嘉義中學
against Taichung No. 1 Middle School
對台中一中的
My father-in-law was the principal at the time
我的岳父那時候做校長之下
so i think it's a great opportunity
所以我覺得這是一個很好的機會
I'll also talk a little bit
我也來稍微講一下
Some thoughts on my research
我的研究的一些心得
The topic I chose today is of course a bit strange
我今天選的這個題目當然是有點奇怪的
because when I'm thinking about something
因為我在想講什麼的時候
I remember several students came to ask me
記得有好幾個學生都來問我
What aspect of current physics research should be done
現在的物理的研究要做哪一方面
Of course it's a big problem
當然這是很大的問題
important question for students
學生很重要的問題
Which aspect of research is better
要做哪一方面的研究比較好
So I probably thought about it a little bit myself
所以我自己大概也稍微想一下
what were those highlights of my past research
我過去的研究的那些重點是什麼
I just realized that I will give two examples today
我就發覺我今天就稍微舉兩個例子
The problem I'm mainly working on is of course related to this
我主要在做的問題當然都是跟這個
This collective behavior is group behavior
這個 collective behavior 就是群體行為
This emerging means
這個 emerging 的就是說
Forever limited in Chinese translation of this word is a bit complicated
永限 在中文翻譯這個字有點複雜
It is related to the emerging behavior called eternal limit
叫永限的 emerging behavior 有關係
In particular I want to get two examples
特別我要取得兩個例子
Of course, it has something to do with quantum and classical
當然是跟這個量子跟古典有關係
The most important question to think about
最重要的這個問題來想
This is the season 19 to 24 from the beginning
從頭來看就是這個 19 到 24 季
Of course physics has made great progress
當然物理學有非常大的進展
especially when most of us
尤其是我們大部分的時候
We already know these important equations
我們已經知道了這幾個重要的方程
Everyone knows the Maxual Equation
Maxual Equation 大家都曉得
Of course, this is very important for the current IT industry
當然這個對現在的 IT industry
All of these are included under the Maxual Equation
所有的這些都是在 Maxual Equation 包含之下的
With this photoelectric conduction all problems
有了這個光電傳導了所有的問題
probably can understand
大概都可以去理解
Just use it in different occasions, in different ways
只是把它用在不同的場合、不同的方式
But another fact, of course we also know about quantum mechanics
但是另外一個當然我們也曉得量子力學的其實
The Schrodinger equation
這個薛丁格方程式
It is the beginning of this important quantum mechanics
它是開始了重要的這個量子力學
Of course, this year's Nobel lecture confirmed the correctness and magic of quantum mechanics
那當然今年的諾貝爾講更是確認了量子力學的正確與神奇性
I'll talk about the magic in a minute
等一下會講一下這個神奇性
is this year's special
是今年的特別
There are many aspects of quantum mechanics that are still incomprehensible
這個量子力學有很多地方還是不能理解
But like Einstein said throwing dice
但是就像愛因斯坦講的是丟骰子
This problem is also confirmed
這個問題也是被確認的
This year, of course, the Nobel lecture was given to something related to this
在今年當然是諾貝爾講是給了跟這個有關的
Then with this dilemma, of course we add Einstein
那有了這個一困境當然我們再加上愛因斯坦
general relativity more than a hundred years ago
一百多年以前的general relativity
Plus Newton's Mechanics
加上Newton的力學
We use Sensory to have all the basic theoretical equations in physics
我們以Sensory在物理學有所有的基礎的理論方程式
Most of the phenomena you just use the theory of these equations
大部分的现象你只要用这些方程式理论
You should be able to gain insight into almost any phenomenon
你应该可以得到了解几乎所有的现象
Or you can predict all phenomena
或者你可以predict所有的现象
The answer is on the other hand
这个答案是另外一方面
Also because we've seen a lot of basic examples
也是因为我们了解了很多的基本的例子
we know all atoms
我们知道所有的原子
what we know about atoms and more
我们了解的原子和等等
The universe is formed from these basic examples
都是由这些基本例子来形成的这宇宙
Then of course why there is this basic example
那当然为什么有这基本例子
that's another mystery
那是另外一个mystery
But at least we know these basic examples
但至少我们知道这些基本例子
can do all kinds of understanding
可以来做各种的理解
So we have the basic ingredients
所以我们有了基本的成分
Plus all table chemistry biomaterials
再加上都起表化学生物材料
any scientific application
任何科学应用
Seems like we've all figured it out
好像我们都解决了问题
So this is what many people say
所以这个从很多人来讲
talk about most of the problems
起来说大部分的问题
we all have it
我们大家全部都有了
should have the answer
应该都有答案
so many people think
所以很多人认为
As long as we understand the table from each state
只要我们了解了每一个州起表的
individual atoms
个别的原子
we can understand all
我们就可以理解所有
Of course this is reductionism
當然這個是reductionism
It is an important direction of science in various disciplines
是現在各個學門科學的一個重要的方向
To put it simply, you only need to start from the basic physical structure
簡單講來講就是你只要從基本的物理結構
Come learn about the many universities that have succeeded in physics
來了解在物理學成功的很多學大學
Now start from some of the most basic equation theory theories
現在都開始從最基本的一些equation theory理論
you can push all kinds of conclusions
你就可以推倒各種的結論
as many scientists believe
就像很多科學家相信
If we knew every gene
我們如果了解每一個基因
we can understand all life phenomena
我們就可以了解所有的生命現象
Of course, now I know that maybe this thought is a bit too naive
這個當然現在知道可能這個想得有點太天真了
And if you use it like this, there is no important problem to solve
還有如果用這樣的話就沒有重要的問題要解決
So I remember around the twenty-first century
所以我記得大概在換二十一世紀的時候
At the end of the twentieth century some theories were that
在那個二十世紀末有些理論就是說
Isn't science already... important science is over
是不是科學已經...重要的科學已經結束了
should know
該知道都知道了
Of course we now know that this is...
當然我們現在曉得這個是...
still far
还远得很
The science we really want to understand is much harder than this
我们真正要了解的科学比这个难多了
But here's at least one interesting question
但这里至少有一个很有趣的一个问题
it's a philosophical question
这是一个哲学的问题
That is, do we use it like this
就是我们是不是用这样子
we can understand all the problems
我们就可以理解所有的问题呢
But now we know this
但是这个现在我们已经知道了
what i want to say today is
我今天要讲的就是
We explored from another direction
我们从另外一个方向发掘
It is these certain phenomena that are possible
就是这些某些现象是可以的
But the most important question we unearth
但是最重要的问题我们发掘
These in each of these complex
这些在每一个组成这些复杂的
The forces between the components of these systems when
这些系统的时候的里面的成分之间的作用力
will produce new phenomena
会产生新的现象
The phenomenon of your merging is that you did not expect it at all
你merging的现象是你原来完全没有想到
is that you understand each element
就是你了解每一个元素
You don't understand new phenomena either, do you?
你也不会了解新的现象会是吗
you have no way of predicting
你没有预测办法
predicted
预测到
That's what we're going to talk about today
那这个是我们我今天要讲的
A few two examples to explain this
几个两个例子来解释这个
Then one of the comparisons is very simple
那这个比中一个很简单的
Of course, if you know carbon
当然就是说你如果知道碳
you know two carbons
你知道两个碳
three
三个
You add in type should understand a lot of carbon
你加在型應該理解很多碳
Of course, let me give you an example here
當然我們這裡我來舉個例子
carbon can be turned into diamond
就是碳可以變成鑽石
It's a very good ghetto. It's hard.
是非常好的絕原體 很硬
But it can also turn into carbon, which is fragile
但是它也可以變成碳 很脆弱
not a very good conductor of electricity
不是很好的電導體
not very good extremist either
也不是很好的絕原體
it can also become graphite creek
它也可以變成石墨溪
it is a good conductor of electricity
它是很好的電導體
Then you can also become carbon nanotubes
那你也可以變成奈米碳管
It is both a conductor and an insulator
它又是導體 又是絕原體
see how you turn it
看你怎麼把它轉起來
you are turning in the wrong direction
你轉的方向不對
it becomes a conductor
它就可以變成導體
Can become extinct
可以變成絕原體
Then your two layers of graphite creek
那你兩層的石墨溪
Can become an insulator, conductor, or superconductor
可以變成絕原體 導體 或超導體
That's the latest research
那這個是最新的研究
then found out
然後就發現
you put these two
你把這兩個
This is a very important contribution of our Vice President Zhou here
這是我們周副院長的很重要的貢獻在這
is when you want to put these two together
就是你要把這兩個放在一起的時候
turned a little
轉了一點
You will find that there is a completely different phenomenon
你就發現完全有不同的現象出現
Everything is not what you imagined, carbon
全部都不是你想像的 碳的
Nothing to do with what I said before
跟前面講的都沒有關係
then this is interesting
那這個就有趣
just something simple
就是很简单的东西
But when there are many things
但是东西很多的时候
put together, many new phenomena appear
放在一起有很多新的现象出现
It's just the easiest
这只是最简单的
but here we still
可是这里我们还
We can probably still understand
已经接着我们大概还可以理解
like this why
像这个是为什么
because we have basic company
因为我们有基本的公司
But here we find
但这里我们就发觉
We're pretty much the latest in the field
我们几乎这是一个最新的领域
There are still many questions we don't know yet
还有很多的问题我们还不曉得
what the hell is going on
到底是这么回事
OK
OK
That's not what we imagined at first
那也不是我们一开始想象到的
what about here
那这里呢
I want to follow a standard
我就要效一个标准的
emerging behavior
emerging behavior
This is almost everyone
这个是几乎大家
This is from youtube
这从YouTube上找来的
There are probably hundreds of thousands of these birds here
这里大概有几十万只这个鸟
it's here
在这里
This is called this, what is it called starling
这个叫这个叫什么叫八哥
The stardings fly here
这个stardings在这里飞
then you can watch its movement
那你可以看它的运动
very interesting
非常有趣
When they act very
他们动作的时候非常
compromise together
妥協在一起
they are moving together
就他们一起在动
I stop this sound
这个声字我把它停掉
The voice behind is incredible
后面的声音是不得了
This was taken at an airport
这个是有人在一个机场拍的
it is very amazing
它是非常惊人的
hundreds of thousands of times
几十万次
But the direction of their fascination seems to be one
但他们迷动的方向好像是一体
So some people are asking how this came about
所以就有人在问了这是怎么形成的
He obviously doesn't have a leader
他明明他没有一个领袖
we little birds are leaderless
我们小的鸟类是没有领袖的
didn't he have a bird take the lead and say
他不是有一只鸟带头说
I should put left, right, up, down
我该放左该右该上该下
he has no leader at all
他完全没有领袖
But his behavior is very clear
但他的behavior非常清楚
they are one in motion
他们是一体在运动
How to achieve such a fast one-piece movement
怎么达到这么快速的一体在运动
This flock of birds is a famous example, along with the flock of fish
这个鸟群跟鱼群都是有名的例子
It is emerging collective behavior
就是emerging collective behavior
is the interaction between the elements
就是元素之间的互相作用
form those special forms
形成那些特别的形式
is not a property of the original element
并不是原来元素有的性质
These are, of course, the so-called definitions
这些这个是当然是所谓的定义
New New King is every element of your original
紐紐景就是你原來每一個元素
Individually have some special properties
個別的時候有些特別的性質
but when added together
但是加在一起的時候
Those properties may have been lost in individual properties
那些性質可能原來個別性質不見了
it has new properties appearing
它有新的性質出現
So wait a minute, these two examples I'm going to give
那等一下我要舉的這兩個例子
The example I'm going to talk about today
我要講的這個今天舉的例子
it has something to do with this
就是跟這個有關係
Then the two examples I gave
那我舉的這兩個例子
Today is one that I have been working on for many years
今天是一個我已經研究很多年的
quantum physics of course
當然是量子物理
The simplest one is, of course, what I want to talk about is the phenomenon of superconductivity.
那最簡單的當然是我要講的是超導的現象
This material superconductivity phenomenon is from top to bottom
這個物質超導現象是由上而下
The so-called top-down means that I already know the basic theory
所謂由上而下就是我已經知道基礎的理論了
Starting from these theoretical models to explain the phenomenon of Yongerjing
由這些理論模型開始去解釋這個永二景的現象
hope is
希望是
But of course we can find that many are beyond our original imagination
但是當然可以發覺很多是超出我們原來的想像
Another example of exactly the opposite is classical physics
那另外一個剛好完全相反的例子是古典物理
Collective phenomenon of cranial nerves
腦神經的集體現象
That's what I've studied for many years
那這個是我研究很多年
In fact, in recent years
其實最近幾年
especially after retirement
尤其是退休以後才真正的話
More time to study is
更多的時間去研究的是
Collective phenomena of the cranial nerves
腦神經的那些集體現象
This is bottom up
這個是由下而上
So the two examples are the exact opposite
所以這兩個例子是完全相反
is that it is generalized from the experimental data
是它是由實驗的數據去歸納
Deriving new physics to advance complete theories
衍生新的物理推進完整的理論
This is of course far from a complete theory.
這個當然還早推倒完整的理論
Just start looking for data now
只是現在開始由數據去尋
new laws of physics
新的物理的規律
Such an approach is, of course, two extreme examples.
這樣子的做法當然就是兩個極端的例子
one is
一個是
And these two examples are actually these two
而且這兩個例子其實是這兩個
In this Emergency Behavior
在這個Emergency Behavior
A real example of two extremes
真正的兩個極端的例子
very extreme example
非常極端的例子
One is that we know very little
一個是我們知道的非常少
one is that we know a lot
一個是我們知道很多
But we still have a lot of new emergency phenomena
但是我們還是有很多新的Emergency現象
is what we're totally groping for
是我們完全在摸索的
unexpected
沒有預料到的
So what about these two examples
所以這兩個例子呢
The two I specifically chose are the ones that happen to be Almost Extreme
我特別選擇的兩個是剛好是Almost Extreme
Counter Exam
Counter Exam
I am a quantity
我一個是量
one is bitter
一個是苦點
The first place that talked about why the instructor chose the instructor at the time can understand
第一个当时讲这个操导为什么选操导的地方就看得懂
This is really an emerging phenomenon
这个真的是emerging的现象
The first example was conducted in 1911, you may have heard
第一个例子当时操导可能大家都听说在1911年
This is the most famous one, which is in the museum
这是最有名的这一张,这是存在博物馆的
This Gentlemen Hike, Camelin Onnes at Lydon University
这位Gentlemen Hike,Camelin Onnes在Lydon University
Last time I visited they had a Museum
我上次去访问他们有一个Museum
There he has this picture, the resistance of his two arches
那里就秀他有这张图,他两个拱的电阻
It is found that at about 4.2 degrees, its resistance becomes very small
发觉到大概4.2度左右,他的电阻变得很小
about 10's of -50's ohms, he jumped 5 orders of magnitude to get here
大概10的-50的欧姆,他跳了5个数量级的到这里
almost like
好像几乎得一般
This question is of course interesting
這個問題當然是很有趣
The question is is it really 0 or almost 0
這個問題是它是真的0還是幾乎是0
It's certainly an interesting question
這當然是很有趣的問題
Because 0 is not a simple number
因為0不是一個簡單的數字
0 is not 0.001
0不是0.001
nor 0.001
也不是0.001
It's just 0 without any decimal point
它就是0 沒有任何的小數點
This is of course a very special number
這個當然是一個很特別的數字
Is it because the experiment is not done well?
到底是因為它實驗做不好
So of course there was a lot of debate when it came out
所以它當初出來當然有很多爭論
Of course it took promise
當然它拿了諾表講
not for this reason
不是因為這個原因
just saw super old
剛看到超老
It uses the Noble watch because it does low-temperature experiments
它拿諾表講是因為它做到低溫的實驗
It lowers the temperature to
它把溫度可以降到
So he was breaking the Guinness Records
所以它那時候是在金式記錄破記錄
lowest temperature
最低的溫度
it reaches the minimum
它達到最低
This is an absolute temperature of 4.2 degrees
這個是絕對溫度4.2度
is now minus 269 degrees
是現在負269度
We set negative 269 degrees
我們設置負269度
OK 269 degrees
OK 269度
terribly cold
冷得不得了
It can achieve this lowest temperature and it finds strange phenomena
它可以做到这个最低温度它就发现奇怪的现象
so it bumps from that
所以它碰条从那
Tell it that it's not because of the discovery of superconductors
跟它拿诺表讲不是因为发现超导体
HV discovers superconductor has no promise yet
HV发现超导体还没有诺表讲
In addition to the high-temperature superconductors that I will talk about later
除了等下会讲的高温超导体
In fact, no one talks about it because of this.
其实没有人拿诺表讲是因为这个
But let's think about it around that time
但是那次周围我们来想一想看
Is it true spirit or almost spirit
这是真的灵还是几乎灵
Of course, let's first understand the mechanism of resistance
当然我们先了解一下电阻的机制
Let me talk about blocking mechanism and this review
我讲点阻机制和这个复习
i think everyone knows
我想大家都知道
You have an electric box
你就有个电子有电盒
It will be a little shocking when it is in motion
它在运动的时候会有些震电
Electricity crash
复电相撞
like atomic boxes and so on or other electrons bumping around
像原子盒等等的或其他电子撞来撞去
Of course, it's quite complicated for you to go from here to here.
那当然你要从这里走到这里还蛮复杂的
you're going to hit a lot of places
你要撞了很多地方
so you have resistance
所以你就有阻力
will create resistance
就会产生阻力
Sometimes it hits you and it hits back and back and back
有时候撞到你就会撞回去再回来撞回去
So this is when you are exercising
所以这个在走运动的时候
it doesn't go in a straight line
它不是走直线的
so simple
那么简单的
So there is resistance
所以就有电阻产生
everyone understands this
这个大家都理解
this is
这个是
Just like liquids have resistance when they flow
就像液体在流动的时候也有阻力
The problem with this is, but this graph
这样子的问题是,可是这个图
But when everyone makes this picture
但到大家做出这个图来的时候
everyone is thinking
大家就想着
The question of whether it is a spirit or not just now becomes very interesting.
刚才讲的是不是灵的问题就变成非常有趣了
Why? These two pictures
为什么?这两个图
This picture I put together two pictures
这个图我是拼了两个图
A green wire is a resistor
一个绿线的是电阻
it slows down with the temperature
随着温度它慢慢下来
When it reaches a temperature we call the temperature of the spirit world
到一个温度我们叫做灵界温度的时候
it becomes spirit, descends to spirit
它就变成灵了,降到灵
But the other line draws the heat capacity
但另外一个线是画的是热容量
What is heat capacity?
热容量是什么呢?
That is to say, if you add a nine-hour heat
就是说你如果加一个九尔的热量
how many degrees will it heat up
它温度会升几度
Every material is different
每个材料都不一样
Its temperature rises and rises like water
它的升长了,升高的温度像水
Everyone thinks to add a lot of heat and it will rise by one degree
大家就想着要加很多热量它会升一度
OK, some of them are easy to upgrade
OK,那有的就很容易升度
That temperature rise
那这个升温度的
change with temperature
随着温度的变化
How much hot dust can be absorbed by its heat capacity
它热容量可以吸收多少热尘的深度
are different
是不一样的
Then this picture, why show this picture?
那这个图,为什么秀这个图呢?
Don't explain it in this picture, why?
这个图也不要解释它,为什么这样?
But this graph has a very special idea
但这个图有一个很特别的想法
So at this point it suddenly gets bigger and smaller
所以在这一点它忽然变大又变小
I'll tell you this right away
那这个马上就告诉你
Above and below this temperature
这个温度的以上跟以下
The material will change
这个材料还要变了
This material is not the original material
这材料不是原来的材料
below this temperature
在这个温度以下
Because it suddenly has a completely different
因为它忽然之间有一个完全不一样的
Variations with temperature
随着温度变化的情况
so you think
所以你就想到
This is actually
这个其实是
If you know that water turns into steam
如果知道水跟变成蒸气
This also has a similar behavior
这个也有类似的behavior
when a similar phenomenon
类似的现象的时候
know it's a phase change
知道这是一个相变
phase transition
叫相转变
But this temperature is called transboundary temperature
但这个温度就叫凌界温度
These are two crossing points towards the middle
就是两个向中间的凌界点
is a boundary temperature
是一个凌界温度
The middle makes water change from liquid to gas
中间让水从液体变成气体
is 4100 degrees
是4100度
So everyone knows it's a transboundary temperature
所以大家知道那是一个凌界温度
here is a problem
这里有一个问题
Of course the two are not exactly the same
当然这两个不是完全一样
but almost
不过差不多
So I use this to say
所以我用这个说
For example, everyone is familiar with
举例大家比较熟悉
but here to tell you
可是这里就告诉你
it is a phase transition
它是一个相转变
So this metamorphosis
所以这个变灵
may be real spirit
可能是真的灵
because it has a phase transition
因为它是有个相转变的
it's not almost 0
它不是幾乎是0
If there is no phase inversion surface
如果這裡沒有一個相轉面
It's very likely that you didn't do the experiment well.
就很可能你這實驗沒做好
This problem is of course now often when new superconductors are discovered
這個問題當然現在常常有新的超導體發現的時候
This question should be fried
這個問題都要炒
Did you really see a superconductor or a fake?
到底你是真的看到超導體還是假的
This problem is all
這個問題是都有
Of course, there are other experiments
當然下面還有別的實驗可以
But this experiment tells you very clearly
可是這個實驗非常清楚的告訴你
there is a horizontal
這裡有一個橫
there is a Xiangtai
有一個向太
And this Xiangtai has entered a new state
而且這個向太是進入一個新的態
it's high temperature
就它高溫的
arch
拱
The situation is completely different from its low temperature situation
的情形跟它低溫的情形是完全不一樣
is another situation
是另外一個情況
It changes the whole system
它整個系統變
when this changes
在這個變的時候
it suddenly becomes 0
它一下子變成0
this is of course interesting
這個當然很有趣
like i just said 0
像我剛講0
not 0.0000
不是0.0000
is 0
是0
That's a Magic Number
那是一個Magic Number
this is
這個是
I remember a long time ago I read a book
我記得很早以前我看過一本書
Chinese before
中國人以前
When using zero, don't use zero
用零的时候不用零的
Chinese don't have zero
中国人没有零
In the beginning, the Chinese had both positive and negative
中国人一开始是有正有负
jump over zero
碰到零就跳过去
I don't want to write this zero
不想要怎么写这个零
this zero is one
这个零是一个
Jiexun is one
捷循当中是一个
indian mathematician
印度的数学家
raised zero
提出来的零
then this zero
那这个零
Ten out is very special
Ten out的是非常特别
In fact, this is of course very related to quantum
那事实上这个当然是跟量子非常有关
Because zero is like zero one two three
因为零是就跟零一二三
Precise
非常准确
not zero zero one
不是零点零零一
either have
要么就有
or nothing nothing
要么就是没有没有什么
almost likely to have
几乎有可能有
ok
ok
he is very sure
他是非常确定的
then here is
那这里就是
Let this happen as soon as he comes out
让这个现象当他一出来
Once confirmed, it is known that this is a quantum phenomenon
确定以后就晓得这是一个量子现象
You have entered a quantum state
你进入一个量子态了
This is known immediately from a
这个就马上就知道从一个
state of classical physics
古典物理的态
It can be said that it has entered a quantum state.
可以这样子讲进入一个量子态了
up the system
在系统往上变
Then this is of course at a very low temperature
那这个当然在很低的温度
Very high temperature, is it possible for four temperatures
很高的溫度,四溫有沒有可能
After 46 years of hard work
那經過46年的努力
Physicists have finally come up with a theory to explain this phenomenon
物理學家總產想出了一個理論來解釋這個現象
Then of course how many arguments went through
那當然中間經過多少的爭論
Find the most famous of these three is
找遍這三位大家最有名的就是
Badin, Kupp, Xu Ruifu
巴丁、庫普、徐瑞弗
Those three came up with a theory in 1957
那三位提出一個理論1957年
They gave a lecture on this theory in 1972 with a Noble watch
他們1972年拿諾表講關於這個理論
To explain this phenomenon of manipulation
來解釋這個操導的現象
Well, this theory is of course for everyone to see.
那這個理論當然是大家可以看
There are so many new concepts that have changed many minds
有太多新的觀念改變了很多的想法
That also explains the phenomenon of this manipulation very clearly.
那也解釋了這個操導的現象非常清楚
this is an outstanding job
這是一個傑出的工作
When I went to Buwang University to study for a Ph.D.
當年我去布王大學念博士的班的時候
It's time for graduate school
是念研究所的時候
In fact, before I went there, I went to the American library
其實那時候我去以前我還上美國圖書館
USIS
美國新聞處
There are many interventions in American universities to check in this way
有很多這個干預美國大學這樣去查
he was at brown university
他在布朗大學
So I originally wanted to find him as a directing professor
所以我那時候本來是想去找他做執導教授的
Leon Cooper
Leon Cooper
Say what you say
說來話算
But after I went there I found out
但是我去了以後才發覺
People told me he doesn't do physics research
人家跟我講他不做物理的研究
He started doing neuroscience at that time
他那時候開始就做neuroscience
just do neuroscience
就做神經科學
I am the same as I am now
我跟我現在一樣
Probably because people start doing neuroscience research when they get old
大概是人老了就開始做神經科學的研究
this is very interesting
這個非常有趣
I can't help if he doesn't do this
他不做這個我也沒辦法
Then I had to change to another professor
後來我就只有換另外一位教授
but anyway
但是不管怎麼講
At that time it turned out that shepherd went to brown university
那時候原來是牧他民而去布朗大學
The explanation of this theory is very explanatory
這個理論的解釋非常解說
He not only explained the mechanism of superconductivity
他不但解釋了超導的機制
Why is there superconductivity
為什麼會有超導
for what reason
用什麼原因
Also understand the quantity-mass state of superconductivity
也了解了超導的量質態
Simultaneously address two major issues
同時解釋兩個重大的問題
their explanation is simple
他們的解釋很簡單
because of superconductivity
就是超導的原因
The first reason is
第一個原因是
The two batteries become a pair
這兩個電池變成一對
called Cooper pair
叫做Cooper pair
Cooper Coober vs.
Cooper Coober對
That's Mr. Cooper just now
就是剛才那位先生Cooper
He proves two batteries
他證明兩個電池
when up and down
一上一下的時候
one he chooses
一個他有自選
Everyone knows that there is an optional battery
電池大家都曉得有一個自選
he turns left or right
他左轉或右轉
Clockwise transfer or anti-clockwise transfer
順時中轉或反時中轉
he has two choices
他有兩個選擇
Which one do you want him to choose?
那你不要他選擇哪一個
but he can
但他都可以
but there are two
但是有兩種
one up and one down
有一個上的一個下的
The two of them like to form a couple
他們兩個喜歡形成一對
This pair is paired up and down
這個一對上下配對
It's called Cooper pair
就叫做Cooper pair
It's an incredibly important job
這是一個很不得了的重要的工作
This work broke through at once
這個工作一下子就突破了
many questions
很多的問題
After this job comes out
那這個工作出來以後
He said it was due to this reason
他就說那是由於這個原因形成
Fried to Taiwan
炒到台
all electricity will do
所有的電都行
Of course this problem is troublesome
那當然這個問題是麻煩的
have a problem
有一個麻煩
Because both of them are power
因為這兩個都是代電
are the same electricity and
都是同樣的電和
We know that two electricity and
我們曉得兩個電和
the same is exclusive
相同的是排斥的
The Max Equation I just talked about
我剛才講的Max Equation
the old man will know
老頭就知道了
you have no reason
你沒有什麼理由
You two are going to be a couple
你這兩個要變成一對
it is clearly repulsive
它明明是排斥的
Isn't the farther away the better?
離得越遠不是越好嗎
So the question is of course
所以這個問題當然是
Need to find a mechanism immediately
馬上就需要找一個機制
why doesn't it reject
說它為什麼不排斥
become attractive
變成吸引
Will the two of them be attracted to each other?
他們兩個會互相吸引呢
Then they also found the reason
那這個理由他們也找到
They all found the reason
他們都找到這個理由
Of course there is a reason
當然是有了這個理由
Their paper can be completed in one go
他們這個paper就可以一氣呵成
The reason is that
那這個原因就是說
Because this is in the material
因為這個在材料裡面
There are also positively charged nuclei
也有正電核的
The atomic nucleus is positively charged
原子核在的是正電核
electrons are negative
電子是負的
the nucleus vibrates
那原子核會震動
When the nuclei are sometimes too close together
原子核有時候靠太近的時候
It likes negative electrons and likes to go
它就喜歡負的電子就喜歡去
Because there are more positive electricity
因為那裡正電比較多
The positive electron went
那正電的一個電子去了
Another electron also likes to go
另外一個電子也喜歡去
If both charges go it becomes
如果兩個電都去就變成
seems attractive
好像有吸引力了
But their attraction is through
但他們的吸引力是經過
the retarder behind it
它的後面的緩速
caused by the environment
環境造成的
this is interesting
這有趣了
is your environment will affect
就是你的環境會影響
take your original repulsive force
把你原來是排斥的力
become an attraction
變成一個吸引力
more than your original repulsion
超過你原來的排斥力
Then this is of course a
那這個當然是一個
incredible assumption
不得了的假設
Of course, this assumption was later proved
當然這個假設後來是被證明
That's why I didn't get the Nobel Prize until 1972.
所以到1972年才拿諾貝爾獎
Because a lot of time to prove these issues
因為很多時間要證明這些問題
Of course it was later proved
當然後來都證明
this is fine
這個都沒問題
Then this is to make people cry
那這個就說請人哭不開
Then I took this all
那我拿的這個都是
Published a special issue for the last time in 100 years
在100年上一次出了一個專刊
To commemorate this 100 years this
紀念這個100年這個
The diagram used in the special issue of 100 years since the discovery of superconductors
超導體發現100年的專刊裡面用的圖
this is very clear
這個很清楚的
It can be explained roughly by the diagram
就示意圖可以解釋大概
not hurt
傷不好
your environment will attack you
你的環境會攻擊你
extra appeal
額外的吸引力
change your original
改變你原來的
it's interesting
這一點很有趣
It turns out that the two should be mutually exclusive
原來兩個是應該互相排斥
Suddenly they no longer reject
忽然之間他們再也不排斥
That's certainly an interesting question.
那這個當然是很有趣的問題
that's the same problem
那就是同樣的問題
Is that electron the original electron?
那電子是不是原來的電子?
Because logically they want to reject
因為照道理他們要排斥
In fact, the result of this final theory is OK
那事實上這個最後的理論的結果就是OK
tell everyone now
現在跟大家講
He believed that Shenxiu's electrons no longer had the characteristics of the original electrons.
他以神秀的電子已經沒有原來電子的特性
Electron has lost its original characteristics
電子已經沒有它原來的特性
This is the difference of emerging
這個就是emerging的別
I'll talk later
我等一下要講
is that you have a new nature
就是你有新的性質
The original old nature is gone
原來舊的性質已經不見了
This is an interesting example
這個是很有趣的一個例子
that this is not enough
那這個還不夠
Just like this will not be without electrons
光是這樣子也不會沒有電子
It's just a pair, then you can still bump
就是一對以後那還是可以撞
There are walls and tables or bumps
有牆有桌子或有撞
But now I use this as an example
但是我現在用這個來舉例
I always think it's the best
我一直覺得這是最好
I haven't been able to find this on YouTube
我一直沒找到這個YouTube
to manifest this dance
來顯現這個跳舞
I don't know if you have seen the old movies
大家不曉得看過舊的電影沒有
Our older adults used to watch this kind of
我們的年紀大人當年有看這種
this one from russia
這個一位俄國的
artist, who painted this large in Vienna before the nineteenth century
藝術家,他畫的在Vienna的這種大得以前的十九世紀
Big Borum Dancing, Waltz
大的Borum Dancing,Waltz
dance the waltz, these men and women are paired up like this, they're dancing
跳華爾之舞,這些一男一女這樣配對,在跳
And then they'll spin around, and then they'll switch partners
然後他們會轉來轉去,然後他們還會交換舞伴
Jump like this, no matter how you dance
這樣子跳,不管怎麼跳
they never hit the wall table table and each other
他們從來也不會撞到牆壁桌子桌子,互相撞
It is very harmonious along with the music, no matter how you dance, it is very beautiful
那順著音樂非常和諧,怎麼跳都非常漂亮
Two exchanges, how to jump, very harmonious
兩個交換,怎麼跳,非常的和諧
Most importantly, why doesn't he bump around
最重要的,他為什麼不會撞來撞去
Because their steps are very coherent, in harmony, in tune
因為他們的步子都非常coherent,同諧,節調
he won't each other
他不會互相
If there is a person who is faster or slower, he will come out soon
那有一個人要是快一點,慢一點,馬上就要出來了
It’s so big, so I thought that if there are those movies that dance this
那這麼大的,所以當初我覺得如果有那些電影裡面跳這個
That's really amazing, everyone has to practice for a long time
那真的很驚人,每個人都要練很久
Don't bump around, jump very
不要撞來撞去,跳得非常
But if you think about it, now I'm drawing
但是你要想,現在是我在畫的
One is an electron going up and one is going down
一個是向上的電子,一個向下的電子
These two electrons are like this, and they are optimal in the whole material.
這兩個電子就這樣子,在這個整個的材料裡面優
Ten twenty three electrons
十的二十三個電子
sons of ten or twenty
十二十人子
Astronomical numbers are doing this
天文數字都在做這個動作
then exchange each other
然後互相交換
They are exchanging positive and negative
他們互相在交換正的跟負的
Zhi Zhi spin up
正智旋向上
Zhixuan down here to exchange back and forth
智旋向下在這邊交換來交換去
then all jumping
然後都在跳
But they didn't bump into each other
但是他們沒有互相撞
none hit
沒有一個撞
Even if there are tables and chairs, they won't hit each other
有桌子椅子也不會撞
so no electrons
所以沒有電子
This is a quantum state
這是一個量子態
This is an all-seeing quantum state
這是一個全部俱觀的量子態
What's the meaning
什麼意思
It's all electrons working together to do the same thing
就是所有的電子都是在一同做同樣的事情
a fully owned electron
一個完全所有的電子
This is an amazing imagination
這個是很驚人的想像
if you imagine this
如果你想像這點就想
How could such a thing happen in the world
世界上怎麼會有這種事情
How do you make electronics so obedient
你怎麼讓電子都那麼聽話
all do the same thing
統統做一樣的事情
And do it very well
而且做得非常同僑
You have another table and chair
你又別的桌子椅子
Like the thing that produces resistance just mentioned
跟剛才講的會產生電阻的東西
has no effect on it
對它都沒有影響
because it doesn't
因為它沒有
it is on a measuring stand
它是在一個量台
if you're going to hit it
如果你要撞到它的話
it's going to knock it into another gauge
它要把它撞到到另外一個量台
Can't hit
撞不到
That energy is too much
那個能量要太大了
The impact of Huotong is impossible to hit
火通的撞擊是打不到
Of course if you add a lot of force
當然如果你加很大的力量
add some extra power
加一些特別的力量
you will destroy it
你會破壞它
But you can't do it on the platform
但平台的話你沒辦法
It is expressed as this scale
它就表成這個量台
Then you usually apply a small voltage and current
那你通常加了很小的電壓跟電流
it just kept running
它就一直跑了
it doesn't
它沒有
it won't go in
它不會進去
In fact, it has been proved by this experiment
事實上它這個實驗是有證明過
They have done it with a national laboratory in the US
他們有做過在美國有一個國家實驗室
What I did was pass the current through the super tower
做過就是把電流通了在超樓台
flushed it for probably years
給它沖了大概好幾年
That current is always running
那個電流永遠都在跑
it works
就通了
The current starts to take you away from the battery
電流開始把你就把電池拿走
the current keeps running
電流就一直跑
it won't stop
它都不會停了
After running for several years
那這個跑了好幾年以後
they turn off
它們就把關掉了
because it has no
因為它已經沒有
I think I'm a little slow on this
這個我看來我有點慢了
Oops
糟了
What about the electron?
那这个电子呢
His other direction is that he doesn't like external magnetic fields
他另外一个方向是他不喜欢外加磁场
he will cause
他会造成啊
Negative forces in different directions
负相不同的方向的力
Then he went up
然后他上一面上了
This wisdom spin will be more than the next wisdom spin
这智旋会比下智旋多
just if you have
就是如果你有的
some time to dance
有些跳舞的时候
more men than women
男的比女的多
What are some men doing?
那有的男的干嘛
will be smashed over there
就会在那边捣烂了
Ah, this is troublesome
啊这个就麻烦
so they don't like
所以他们不喜欢
Then when you add a magnetic field
那这个你加磁场的时候
don't like
也不喜欢
what about this
那这个怎么办呢
So there is the phenomenon of word service
所以就有词服现象了
this is a magnetic field
这个是一个磁场
This is a superconductor
这是超导体
magnetic field
磁场
This magnet will hang
这个磁铁就会悬起来
magnetic fields he doesn't like magnetic fields
磁场他不喜欢磁场
he gets rid of him
他就把他排掉
You see this is a new phenomenon
你看这个又是一个新的现象
none of us expected
我们都没想到
This is very smart
这个非常聪明啊
If he doesn't like him, get rid of him
他不喜欢他就把他排掉
Exhaust the magnetism to the outside
把磁地排到外面
he floated
他就浮起来了
Then this one is called Massner
那这个是叫Massner一份
Well, this is actually very reasonable and simple
那这个其实很道理很简单
Now we understand that it is simple
现在我们了解到很简单
it's simple
这道理很简单
Farrati's law
就是法拉蒂定律
because you added a magnetic field
因为你加了磁场
he will generate electricity
他就会产生电流
Current is in the opposite direction to magnetic field
電流跟磁場剛好相反的方向
everybody knows
大家都知道
This is Landrow
這是Landrow
in that direction
那個方向的話
It will shield its magnetic field
就會把它磁場給屏蔽掉
Of course it's normal here
當然這裡是跟平常的
Why can't normal iron
為什麼平常的鐵不會呢
Ordinary metal won't
平常的金屬不會呢
because normal metals are
是因為平常的金屬是
current will be gone
電流會不見了
With resistance
有電阻
Disappear under current
電流下就不見了
But this is superconducting
但這個是超導
it won't
它不會
So the superconductor will always have a current
所以超導會一直有電流
keep it blocked
一直把它屏蔽掉
so it will float with great force
所以它就會浮起來力量很大
of course this is
那這個當然是
just said
剛才講的
This is Massiness
這個叫Massiness
But if you then increase the magnetic field
但如果你再把磁場增加
it can't get rid of
它排不掉
too strong
太強了
what about it
它怎麼辦
it puts it in
它把它放進去
how does it go in
它怎麼放進去呢
it puts it in like a gold grid
它把它放得很有金格的放進去
it confines it to a small place
它把它侷限在一個小地方
That dark place over here has a magnetic field
那這邊這黑的地方是有磁場的
There is no magnetic field outside
外面是沒有什麼磁場
This is what they calculate
這個就是他們計算
This Apricot of the Landrow speaks for itself
這位Apricot of the Landrow表而講
because it lifts the math
是因為它解除這個數學
This is called vortex rolling out
這個叫做旋渦旋捲出來
show inside
裡面就秀
It has a magnetic field inside
它裡面是有磁場
The outside is shielded
外面是屏蔽調
OK
OK
so it was very successful
所以它這個非常成功
Received the Nobel Prize in 2003
在2003年拿諾貝爾獎
This result is of course the result of the experiment at the beginning.
這個結果當然是一開始是實驗的結果
very amazing
非常驚人
it will line it up nicely
它會把它排得好好的
this is us to show this
這個是我們來秀這個
The one just mentioned was an experiment.
剛才講的那個是有一個實驗的
oh
喔
I obviously can't do it here
我這裡顯然是沒有辦法做
oops
哎呀
I'll stop now
那我先暫停好了
this is a bit troublesome
這個有點麻煩
I was going to show how it lined up
我本來要秀它怎麼排起來的
but i think i might have to hold it up
但是我看我可能要它扶起來
But there may not be enough time now
可是現在的時間可能不夠了
let me tell you
那我就來講一下
there's something special in here
這裡面有些特別的什麼東西好了
What I just said
剛才講的這個東西
Talking about this nest
講的這個窩懸
talk like this
講的像這個
What about each of these things?
這每一個的東西呢
Actually you
其實你
You see it's neatly arranged
你看排得整整齊齊
But everyone has a fixed unit
但每人都有一個固定單位
all the same size
都大小都一樣
The black dots are all the same size
這黑點的大小都一樣
Then this is called a special quantum magnetic flux
那這個是叫做一個特別的叫做量子磁通量
It has a certain unit
就它是有一定的單位的
what about this unit
這個單位呢
Planck Conson
是普蘭克康森
Double the pad box
除上兩倍的墊盒
Twice the pad box is Couple Pair
兩倍的墊盒是Couple Pair
Couple Pair is two pad boxes
Couple Pair就是兩個墊盒
two chia
兩個恰齊
so two
所以就是兩個
It is H except these two pad boxes
就是H除上這兩個墊盒
It is called a standard Flux mine
就是叫做一個標準的Flux礦堂
it everyone
它每一個人
The black dot I just saw
剛剛才看到的黑點
this is the point
就是這一個點
Then there is no magnetic field in the middle
然後這裡中間是沒有磁場
magnetic field in
磁場通通在
get in the middle of it
被它灌在中間去
next to the current
旁邊有電流
put this magnetic field
把它這磁場都
The magnetic field in the middle is gone
中間的磁場都沒有了
only in a small area
只有聚集在很小的範圍
you can't even imagine
這個你想都想不到
this natural world is wonderful
這個自然界真美妙
This mat seems to have a brand
這墊子好像有Brand那樣
Actually it doesn't have Brand
其實它沒有Brand
But it doesn't hurt well, it will find a way by itself
但它傷不好會自己想辦法
Shrink this magnetic field to a very small distance
把這個磁場縮到很小一個距離裡面
it does not affect
它不要影響到
So most of the place has no magnetic field
所以大部分的地方沒有磁場
It did not affect the steering
它沒有影響到操導
steer it's still there
操導它還在那裡
will not be affected by it
不會被它影響
only a few places
只有很小一些地方
This is the best rounding signal
這是最佳的捨入訊號
think about it
想一想就覺得
it's just incredible
這簡直是不可思議
it will find your best solution by itself
它自己會找到你最好的一個解
Let this rounding information exist
讓它這個捨入訊存在
that this is very small
那這個是很小的
but the thing is it's fun
但是問題是它很有趣
It must have integers likewise
它一定要有整數的同樣
This is a quantity effect
這個又是量的效應
It's not another effect
這又不是別的效應
it must be an integer
它一定要是整數
not an integer not yet
不是整數 還不行
you can count
你可以算
You can count the one just now
剛才那個你可以算
Carrying the Triangular Ginger is fine
抬著三角金格很好
But it must be an integer
但它就是一定要整數
but you can ask
可是你可以問
Then why do I want integers
那我為什麼要整數
I can apply a magnetic field from the outside
我可以從外面加磁場
I added a magnetic field outside
我外面加了磁場
any magnetic field
可以任何磁場
I don't have to be that
我不一定要是那個
The multiple of the magnetic flux just now
剛才磁通量的倍數
multiples of integers
整數的倍數
I can do it 1⁴ can I
我可以它的1⁴可不可以
1⁹ more
多1⁹行不行
Then if more than 1⁹
那如果多1⁹
In fact, there are two possible solutions
其實有兩個可能解
One is that your superconductor produces a clockwise current
一個就是你的超導體產生一個順時電流
add one-half to one
把二分之一加到變成一個
generate a current
自己有產生一個電流
The current starts to run
電流開始跑
add one-half
加二分之一上去
One-half plus one-half becomes one
二分之一加二分之一變成一個
curious
好奇的
But I can run in reverse
但是我可以反向的跑
becomes minus one-half
變成負二分之一
One-half plus minus one-half becomes zero
二分之一加負二分之一變零
I can also be zero
我也可以變成零
I have two possibilities
我有兩個可能性
one running forward
一個往正向跑
a reverse run
一個反向跑
One becomes one and one becomes zero
一個變一一個變零
it's okay
也沒事了
It suits my condition just now
就適合我剛才的條件
It must be an integer multiple
它一定是整數倍了
That is, if you insist on adding half a magnetic head to measure it in
就是你如果硬要加半個磁頭量進去
it can also
它也可以
It can increase the amount of head
它可以加磁頭量
it becomes like this
它就變成這樣
but who is right in the end
但最後誰對呢
Is it one or two
到底是一還是二
The answer is both and neither
答案是兩個都是也都不是
the answer is
這個答案就是
Learn to be a cat
學定個貓了
That is, everyone scanned the superposition state of the two states
就是大家掃了兩個狀態的疊加態
is its answer
才是它的答案
This is Quantum Mechanics
這個就是量子力學
most amazing place
最神奇的地方
This answer is also this year
這個答案也是今年
Did you talk about it?
有沒有講,有重點
This is to learn to determine a Rams, whether it is one or zero, alive or dead
這個是學定個 Rams,到底是一還是零,活的還是死的
You don't know either, both are possible, and both are falling prices
你也不知道,兩個都有可能,兩個是跌價
This is used to make Flox, quantum qubit
這個就是拿來做Flox, quantum qubit
Everyone knows that computers need to use this quantum bit
大家都曉得量著電腦要用這個 quantum bit
The qubit, if calculated by Flox, is made like this
那qubit,如果用Flox來算的話,就是這樣的一個做的
As I said just now, there are superconductors here
就是剛才講,這邊都超導體
Then you have to pass through inside, the magnetic momentum must pass through, it must be an integer number
那你裡面要經過,那個磁動量要經過,一定是要整數個
I didn't talk about it just now, so it must be an integer
剛才不是講,所以它一定是整數個
In it it can do the Flox qubit
在這裡面它就可以做Flox qubit
Then if you say, if two qubits are placed next to each other today
那你如果說,今天如果把兩個qubit擺在旁邊
I only put a magnetic momentum into it
我只擺一個磁動量進去
It's one is one on the left and zero on the right, or one on the right and zero on the left
它一的是左邊是一,右邊零,或者是右邊是一,左邊是零
it only has two possibilities, right
它只有兩個可能,對不對
It is impossible for both to be one and zero at the same time
不可能兩個都同時一,同時零
Zero and one, because put one in
零零一,因為擺一個進去
What is the sum of these two? This is this year's
那這兩個加起來是什麼?這個就今年的
I don't want to appeal
我不要呼籲一下
This is today's entanglement
這就是今天的今天的intanglement
this proof
這個證明
If you put these two
如果到時候你把這兩個
These two Q ratios are far apart
這兩Q比離得很遠
it's still the same
它都還是一樣
If you measure to one
如果你邊量到是一
The other side must be zero
另外一邊就一定是零
because zero is one
因為零就一
this is very simple
這個很簡單
But this is beyond
但這個就是超到
Of course, today's quantum computers
當然現在的量子電腦
Mainly use super to body
主要都是用超到體在做
I won't talk about this anymore
這個我就不再講了
But this PCS theory
但這個PCS理論
is a giant quantum effect
是呈現個巨觀的量子效應
However, some of the original properties are no longer displayed
但個別原來的性質已經不顯示出來
only group sex
只有群體的性
So what I said just now is the behavior of groups
所以我剛才講都是群體的行為
Neither one or two electronic acts
都不是一兩個電子行為
All electrons do these things
所有的電子都在做這些事情
Do together
一起做
that's a strange thing
那就是很奇怪的一個事情
but it is very beautiful
但它是非常漂亮的
sexual behavior
性體行為
but in it
但是在這裡面
Of course there are bigger problems
當然是有更大的問題
is it possible for you to say
就是你有沒有可能說
There is a Coopers Pass formed
有形成Coopers Pass
have no homology
都沒有同條性
it's too strong
就它太強了
Just now I said that I am in a team, so I have no electrons
剛才講我是成隊,我就變成沒有電子
Can't I form a team first without having the same article?
我是不可以先成隊,而沒有同條性呢?
As I said earlier, if the room is large, many people will dance
像剛才講,如果房間很大,很多人要跳舞
The people over here have already started to dance, but the people over there haven't danced yet
那這邊的人已經開始跳了,那邊的人還沒跳
Then there is no same article
那不是就沒有同條了
Some people dance here at different paces
那有的人在這邊跳舞是不同的步伐
Someone is different here, different on both sides
有人在這邊不一樣,兩邊都不一樣
That has CooperPet , but no conformity
那都有CooperPet,但是沒有同條性
Then there is no way to become a non-electric group.
那就沒有辦法變成無電組了
It's not over-falling, then this phenomenon has never been seen before.
就不超倒,那這個現象以前是沒有看到的
But in this 1987
但是在這個1987年
These two Gentlemen in October
這兩位Gentlemen在10月的時候
In September, there was PayFer
89月的時候有編PayFer
It's going to be a very exciting start to November with a new super-down
到11月的時候就開始非常精彩的開始有新的超倒
After that, Wu Maokun and I found YBCO
那出經我跟吳茂坤就找到YBCO
They were the first to look for it, and they won the Nobel Prize in the second year
他們是最早找,他們拿第二年就拿諾貝爾獎
ok it's very early
ok 這是非常早的
As early as the second year, the material was brought out to talk about it.
早到材料第二年就拿出來講的
This is the high-level conductor
就是這個高文操導體
At that time, of course, there was another important
那那個時候當然還有一個重要的
I also went to participate
我也去參加了
I don't know if Mei Yini went there at that time
不曉得美英尼那時候有沒有去
At the March Meeting in New York in 1987
在1987年在紐約的March Meeting
I will go to participate
我就去參加
it was 12 o'clock in the evening
那時候是晚上12點
it's 12 o'clock at night
這是晚上12點
crazy for physicists
對物理學家都發瘋了
in the squeeze
在擠單那裡
There is still a meeting at 12 o'clock in the evening
晚上12點還在開會
It's been a day
已經開了一天的會
I still have to go to the crowded hall to give a speech tonight.
晚上還要去擠廳那個演講
About Gawain
關於高文操導
This is WooStar
這叫WooStar
WooStar is chasing hot singers in the past
WooStar就是在以前追逐熱門歌手
star party
明星的聚會
At that time we also did
那個時候我們也做了
Then why am I talking about this?
那這個我為什麼要講這個呢
This is the Gawain conductor
這是高文操導體
there is a special phenomenon
是有一個特別的現象
It's supposed to be a special material
就是它本來應該是一個特別的材料
time it should be a strong force
是時候它應該是有很強的作用力
it was supposed to be a conductor
它本來應該是一個導體的
Turns out it's an insulator
結果它是一個絕緣體
Then this picture is a
那這個圖是一個
In fact, this picture is too complicated
我其實這個圖太複雜
I won't drop you either
也不掉你們
but i just want to tell you
但是我只要告訴你
This picture is from a review in 2003
這一張圖是2003年一個review的
Talk about the picture at that time
說那時候的相圖
At that time they thought that high temperature superconductivity should look like this
那時候他們認為高溫超導應該是這樣子像
but now this half
但是現在這一半
They only showed half of it, it's too complicated
他們只秀了這一半已經複雜太多了
By 2017, this phase diagram has become much more complicated than this
到2017年這個相圖就變得比這個複雜太多了
High-temperature superconductivity is always a very complicated phenomenon
高溫超導得永遠都有很複雜的現象
keeps appearing
一直出現
so far there are
到現在為止還有
But the most interesting is the question
但最有趣的是這個問題
in this state
在這個態呢
It seems to have cried, but it is not superconducting
好像是有哭過對但不超導
superconducting below this not superconducting above this
超導在這個下面在這上面不超導
Non-superconducting states do exist
不超導的態確實存在
I just cried
就是有哭過對
that's what i just said
就是我剛才講的
it already has a pair
它已經有成對了
Then here I just show some measurement results
那這裡我只秀一下一些測量的結果
What about their materials?
他們這裡的材料呢
It uses STM
它是用STM
STM is a needle tip of my electric current
STM就是我家電流一個針尖
Like a tip, when I pass a voltage, there will be a current
像個尖我通了電壓就會有電流
The change in current follows the change in voltage
那電流的變化跟隨著電壓的變化
You can see how the electrons on this surface
你可以看出這個表面上的電子是怎麼樣
how different electronic states
也是怎么不同的电子态
like here
像这里呢
it goes from here to here
它从这里往这里走
its electronic state is changing
它的电子态在变
With voltage
随着电压
So the current is changing
所以电流在变
What about this state?
那这个态呢
it shows
它就显示出
you have two electrons here
你当这里有两个电子
Positron
正电子
it has flaws
它放着缺陷
This this Calsium
这个这个Calsium
cover is two
盖是两架
Usually it sends two electrons
通常它送了两个电子
but if you are defective
但是你如果有缺陷
it becomes two less
它就变成少了两个
put two electrons
放两个电子
Just two positive boxes
就两个正电盒
There are two positive boxes near this
在这个附近有两个正电盒
Two positive boxes become
两个正电盒就变成
look like this
长成这个样子
so it this is
所以它这个是
What about the experiment?
实验呢
is showing
是显示出
I just put two electric boxes in it
我只放两个电盒进去
you will form
你就会形成
It seems that a very strange shape is at the entrance of the building
好像一个很奇怪的形状在楼口
Then if you put two pairs
那你如果放两对的时候
it will form more complex phenomena
它就会形成更多复杂的现象
Its two pairs will layer horizontally into one large
它两对会横层变成一个大的
what if i have 12 pairs today
那如果我今天有12对呢
put it all together
通通放在一起
what have you become
你又变成什么样呢
if i have 10
我如果有10的
ten times right?
十次方对呢
ten targets
十的
20 squares right?
20式方對呢
but you will suffer
可是你都會有苦薄對
but no homology
但沒有同條性
it's already bitter
就它已經有苦薄對了
This is the result of the experiment
這個是實驗的結果
why show this
為什麼要秀這個呢
is when you put 10 to 20 squares
就是當你放10到20式方對
you realize
你就發覺
Wow
哇
it's arranged in a special shape
它排得很特別的形狀
It's inside the building
就是它樓口內
with these bitter pairs
有這些苦薄對
but it doesn't necessarily have the same
但它不見得有同條性
There is zero electricity
有零電
that's a new phenomenon
那這就是新的現象
It turns out that the BCS theory doesn't fit well again.
原來BCS理論又不太合了
totally different story
完全有different story
What about this story?
那這個story呢
important modern research
就是現代的重要的研究
then this is to tell you
那這個就是告訴你
It's more complicated than we thought
比我們想像的還複雜多了
real emerging behavior
真正的emerging behavior
more
還更多了
I just talked a little bit about it
那我剛剛只是稍微講到一點
That high-security has been developed for 36 years and has been used continuously
那高安發達了36年不斷用
the most important reason
最重要的原因
Its electronic construction is very strong
它電子建作用力非常強
with a lot of new emerging behavior
用很多new emerging behavior
As I just said, there are new ones every year
我剛才講的每年都有新的
still not finished
還有還沒完
You haven't finished frying this material, there are too many new things
大家还没炒完这个材料太多新的东西
Then we don't find out what to do
那我们不找到怎么处理
The above theories are all top-down
那以上的理论都是由上而下
that's what i just said
就是我刚刚讲
we have basic couple pair
我们有基本的couple pair
Just this idea superconducting
就这个idea超导
Then I go like this
然后我就这样子去
try to apply it to more complex phenomena
试着要把它应用到更复杂的现象
But some are successful and some are not
但是有的成功有的不成功
OK
OK
The other is to say
那另外一个就是说
it's us
就是我们
That is, we work from the bottom up
就是我们是由下而上
just look at the data
完全只看数据
the most famous example
那最有名的一个例子
I now give this example
我现在举这个例子
Take the example of the flock of birds just now
就刚才那个鸟群的例子
how do physicists understand it
物理学家怎么理解它呢
do the dumbest way
做最笨的方法
take pictures
照相
take a quick photo
用快速照相去照
when every bird is flying
每一个鸟在飞的时候
what is its direction
它的方向是什么
it is the direction of velocity
它是速度的方向
OK
OK
this is speed
这是速度
then its direction
然后它的方向
Take the image volume of this speed and put it
把这个速度的像量把它
Find out, and then ask whether these two directions are related
找出來,然後問這兩個方向有沒有關聯性
just do this
就做這個事情而已
Because of this matter, the data is analyzed, and then a model is fit
因為這個事情數據去分析,然後去fit一個模型
The model is like this, only these two quantities
模型就是這樣,只有這兩個項量
For example, for each bird, there are about eight birds beside it
比如說每一個鳥,看它旁邊大概有八隻鳥
This NC is good, let's say eight are good
這個NC好了,說八隻好了
Ask about the relationship between the eight birds next to it and it
問它旁邊八隻鳥跟它的關聯性
Then you do it, just write it as a simple model
然後你就算,就把它寫成一個簡單的模型
They did it and it turned out to be
他們就去做,結果turned out to be
this professor did
這個教授做的
Let’s talk about that APS
這個拿那個APS講
This work is very beautiful, after finishing
這個工作非常漂亮,做完了以後
This is too simple, more simple idea
這個是太簡單的,更簡單的想法
I just go to fit
就是我就去fit
Turns out the bird-to-bird relatedness is a borderline
結果發覺這些鳥跟鳥的關聯性是一個臨界狀態
Just now I have talked about what is called the critical state, in the middle of two phases
剛才我已經講了什麼叫臨界狀態,在兩個相中間
they're on edge
他們就在臨界狀態
This is of course, why he is on edge, no one knows
這個當然是,為什麼他在臨界狀態,沒有人知道
but he's on edge
但他就是在臨界狀態
And it's a very beautiful critical state
而且是非常漂亮的臨界狀態
this is a very interesting
這個是一個很有趣的
But the state of this part is of course the most important reason, we can explain it with this iron pool
但是這個零件狀態當然是最重要的原因是我們可以解釋是用這個鐵池來解釋
Everyone knows that iron pools are magnetic at low temperatures
鐵池大家都曉得低溫的時候都有磁性
But at high temperature, if you raise the iron pool to high temperature, there will be no magnetism
但高溫的時候你如果把鐵池升加高溫就沒有磁性了
Each magnetic transition up or down
每一個磁的轉變上或下
like we say one or minus one
像我們這句說一一或負一
You can down and up be one plus one or minus one
你可以下上是一正一或負一
But if you are in very high temperature
但是如果你在很高溫的時候
Each magnetic spin can be up or down at will
每一個磁旋都可以隨便上一或負一
so it adds up to zero
所以加起來是零
when you're cold
在你在很低溫的時候
Each magnetic spin tries to be the same as the one next to it
每一個磁旋盡量想跟它旁邊的一樣
These two have the same lower energy
這兩個一樣的能量比較低
These two are different, the energy is higher
這兩個不一樣能量就比較高
it doesn't like
它就不喜歡
so it likes to be with it
所以它喜歡跟它一樣的在一起
Then this is Ice in model
那這個是Ice in model
This is a very simple model
這個是很簡單的一個模型
called the Ice in magnetic spin model
叫做Ice in 磁旋模型
So everyone in the literature has probably learned this
所以學物裡的大概都學過這個
up or down
向上或向下
Then this model it is very simple
那這個模型它是很簡單
There's a weird thing about this model
這個模型可是有一個很奇怪的地方
You can imagine black going up and white going down
你可以想像黑的就向上白的向下
Then this is a very messy and disorderly image.
那這個是一個很雜亂無序的象
But at low temperature
但是在低溫的時候呢
What about when it's cold?
這個在低溫的時候呢
it will be more and more like it will be
它會越來越多的象會一樣
more and more white
白的會越來越多
There will be fewer and fewer black pictures like this one
像這個圖黑的會越來越少
Of course, there may be more and more black
當然也可能黑的越來越多
less and less white
白的越來越少
but it's all possible
但是它都可能
But when you are at part temperature
可是你在零件溫度的時候
will find a strange phenomenon
就會發現一個奇怪的現象
it's not much white
它不是白的多
less black
黑的少
White, black, not much difference
白的黑的差不了太多
but
但是呢
it's always big
它永遠都很大
The white one is also big
白的也很大一塊
The black one is also big
黑的也很大一塊
There is black in the middle of the white
那白的中間有黑的
The black ones look carefully and there are white ones inside
黑的在仔細看裡面又有白的
become complicated
變得很複雜
It's different from the low temperature
跟原來這個低溫的不一樣
Of course it's not the same as high temperature
跟高溫當然跟不一樣
Each independent black and white is completely random
每一個都獨立的黑白是完全random
Then this phenomenon can be explained
那這個現象是可以解釋的
And it was Ansack who explained it back then.
而且是安薩克當年解釋出來的
This is in the middle of order and disorder
這個就是在有序跟無序向的中間
In this zero-medium state neither is the case
就這個零介態既不是這樣的
It's not what I just said
也不是剛才講的
It is also not ordered in the middle of two
它在兩個中間也不是有序
it's right in the middle right here at this point
它就在這中間就在這一點
The disordered direction means zero on average at high temperature
無序向就是高溫的時候平均是零
because half up and half down
因為一半向上一半向下
the odds are the same
機率是一樣
But at low temperatures almost all upward
但在低溫幾乎都向上
you're not so sure at this temperature
在這溫度你不是很確定
it's up some up
它有些向上有些向上
so it's not a special
所以它不是一個特別的
right at the boundary of the two faces
就在兩個面的界限
it looks like both up and down
它看起來像都向上也有向下
but it's not quite
但是它不是完全如此
it's a strange state
這是一個奇怪的態
Then this strange state is a state of concealing the mirror
那這個奇怪的態是一個隱瞞鏡的狀態
Then of course it is here
那這裡當然就是
If you look at the correlation distance
如果你去看關聯距離的話
Associated functions Both are associated functions
關聯函數兩個都關聯函數
Usually there is an association distance
通常有个关联距离
There is no association beyond the association distance
超过关联距离就没有关联
But low temperature and high temperature have a correlation distance
但低温高温都有关联距离
But there is no correlation distance at midnight temperature
但在凌夜温度的时候没有关联距离
The association distance is infinite
关联距离是无限大
that this is very interesting
那这个是很有趣
This first one, this math is of course a bit
这个第一个这个数学当然有点
If you know that this is in the form of an exponential
如果大家知道这是指数的形式
Then this is when Tc
然后这个是Tc的时候
it is density
它是密率
ok
ok
it has no size
它没有尺寸
fractal
fractal
It behaves completely differently
它的表现是完全不一样的
I just said that the flock of birds is in this phenomenon.
刚才讲鸟群就在这个现象
I'll get to this quickly now
那我现在就快一点讲到这个
The biggest problem is that there are a lot of
那最大的问题是这个里面有很多的
special phenomenon
特别的现象
Just at this Tc time
就在这个Tc的时候
It becomes infinite in many things
它很多东西都变成无限大
If an infinite system
如果是无限大的系统
not infinite system
不是无限大系统
it gets big
它就变得很大
Then I will summarize it
那这个我就把它summary
just talked too much
就刚才讲的太多
Maybe everyone will be the first to have a meal reserve
可能大家会第一个有个蓄餐量
at high temperature it is not
在高温它是没有的
Infinity at low temperature
无限在低温的话
it is
它是
Ordered and disordered in the middle to an intermediate state in the middle
有序中间都无序到中间有一个中间界态
This state is a special state
这个态是特别的态
Then this state is an emerging state
那这个态是一个emerging state
It's not surprising that everyone goes up
大家都向上也不稀奇
like we have spin
就像我们有spin
two just two together
两个就两个在一起
he also likes to go up
他也喜欢向上
So not too new emerging station
所以不是太新的emerging台
It's not unusual to turn around
乱转也不稀奇
there are many words
有好多个的话
Of course there are some who don't like to go up
当然有一些是不喜欢向上
he goes up
他就向上
but at high temperature
但是在高温的时候
stand in this position
站在这个态
he's weird
他就很奇怪了
His association training is infinite
他的关联训是无限远的
he has no distance
他没有距离的
That is to say, you are in the ratio of one centimeter to two centimeters
就是说你在一公分到两公分的比例
The ratio of one meter to two meters
跟一公尺跟两公尺的比例
100km is the same as 200km
100公里跟200公里的比例都是一样的
OK
OK
he makes no difference
他没有差别
he doesn't care how far you are
他不管你多远
his mutual size
他的互相的大小
all the same size
尺寸都是一样
So this is what I just said
所以这个就是刚才讲的
Fractal Self-Similarity
Fractal Self-Simularity
that question
那这个问题
let's talk
我们就来讲一下
The question I was going to talk about today
我本来今天要讲的这个问题
Pity
可惜了
to talk about this mind
要讲这个脑神
so big, and the cerebellum has so many neurons
那麼大的,然後小腦有這麼多神經元
how do we understand
我們怎麼理解?
That's all Guoyi's mind is
果衣的腦子就這麼一點
How to understand the brain?
怎麼去理解腦?
Of course someone made one
那當然有人做了一個
I'll talk a little bit quickly
我稍微很快講一下
did an experiment
做了一個實驗
how to do it
是怎麼做呢?
this is an interesting experiment
這個是很有趣的實驗
Everyone knows to use VR to play
大家都曉得用VR去玩
when game play
當game玩
But the New York Science of Physicists
但是物理學家的紐約Science
It is used to show the old
是拿來做給老所看
This VR video
這個VR的影片
make him think he's running outside
讓他以為他在外面跑
In fact, the old man is running on this ball
其實老所在這個球上面跑
But he has a camera on his head
但他頭上裝了個camera
Can videotape his brain lights up
可以錄影他的腦神經在發亮
lights up when he sees something
他看到什麼東西的時候在發亮
Showed him some illusions
給他看的是一些假象
He has been running and watching
他一直在跑一直在看
Then the brain keeps recording
然後腦就一直記錄
It's an amazing experiment
這是非常驚人的實驗
beautifully done
做得很漂亮
You didn't expect to do such a beautiful experiment
你沒想到做得那麼漂亮的實驗
He looks at the brain
他看腦神經
What does it have to do with what he saw?
跟這個他看到的東西有什麼關聯性
This is
這就是
data to be tested
要做實驗的數據
data we make
我們做的數據
I made it very simple with a professor
我跟一個教授做很簡單
very cheap
很便宜的
Put a small camera on the head of the mouse
就把老鼠頭上帶一個小的camera
Called Mini scope
叫Mini scope
So it was Professor Wu Dongchuan who worked at China Medical University
所以是吳東川教授在中國醫藥大學做
then give him a
那就給他在一個
run inside the barracks
軍營裡面跑
You see he's selling too
你看他也在發販
so we can keep track of which cowherds are selling
所以我們可以記錄哪些牛郎在發販
Which cowherds are selling
哪些牛郎在不在發販
we have data
我們有數據
Just like this is a very delicate matter
就跟這個是很精密的事
This is a very famous thing
這是很出道的事
This is probably Cadillac
這個大概就是Catilac
This is probably a cheap car
這個大概是很便宜的車子
this is
這個是
this result
這個結果
the result we made
我們做出來的結果
I don't talk anymore
我也不講了
just to tell you yes
就是給你講說是
What we end up with is almost the same
我們最後得到的結果是幾乎一樣
is found
是發覺
in these phenomena
在這些現象
see the experiment
看到實驗的現象
are in Critical state
都是在Critical state
are near the critical temperature
都在臨界溫度附近
That is, the temperature of the experiment is T1
就是實驗的溫度是T1
the temperature of the experiment
就實驗的溫度
But we use this to analyze
但是我們用這個去分析
Other data we found that it is almost all in the part temperature
其他数据我们发觉它几乎都是在零件温度
This is very complicated data made with others
这个跟别人做的很复杂的数据
It's the same for others to do very complex data
别人来做很复杂的数据是一样
What we do is a very simple debut of the data
我们做的是非常简单的出道的数据
But the answer is almost exactly the same
但是答案几乎完全一样
This is a very interesting phenomenon
这个是很有趣的一个现象
This phenomenon doesn't make much sense from physics.
这个现象当中从物理学里面也没什么意思
If the part phenomenon
如果在零件现象
It's not quite Depend on detail
它不太Depend on detail
Many details are not important
很多detail是不重要的
It only cares about some important parameters of this long distance
它只关心这长距离的一些重要的参数
Here we use very debut measurements and very precise measurements
这里用很出道的测量跟用很精确的测量
In the end the answer is that all the rats are running around here
最后答案就是所有的老鼠在这里跑来跑去
His brain behaves as if he cares about the pie of some parts
他的脑神经的表现好像在意某些零件的派
Why is it important to be there
为什么在那里是一个很重要的
This is of course a lot of RESET below us doing this problem
這當然是我們下面的很多的RESET在做這個問題
But at least this is an interesting phenomenon
但是至少這個是一個有趣的現象
before our eyes
在我們眼前
Then this is a show
那這個是秀就是說
You didn't expect such a simple question
你沒想到那麼簡單的一個問題
unexpectedly get such a strange result
居然會得到一個這麼奇怪的結果
But my conclusion is that when the elemental effect becomes very strong in a large group
但是我的結論就是當很大的群體中元素作用變得很強勢
New Emergy behavior becomes
新的Emergy行為成
These behaviors often require new laws and principles
這些行為往往是需要新的規律與原則的
That's of course what I'm quoting is the supervisors
這就是當然這點我引用的是這位監督們
PW Anderson
PW Anderson
He died two years ago and this is the Nubai Prize winner.
他兩年前去世這位是努拜獎得主
his proposed book
他的提出來的有本書
Paper, The More is Different
Paper, The More is Different
If you go Beyond Nature
如果你Go Beyond Nature
Nature has a Hierarchist Structure Science
Nature有一個Hierarchist Structure Science
Science does not mean that you are always the most basic
Science不是說你總是最基本的
You will know all about Science
你就會了解所有的Science
layer by layer structure
一層一層的結構
Layer by layer the phenomenon is different
一層層的現象是不一樣的
Need different principles to explain
需要不同的如同的principle去解釋的
Here are a few questions I just raised
那這裡我剛才舉的幾個問題就是
In fact, to tell everyone
其實就是告訴大家
Turns out what we know isn't quite resolved
原來我們知道的並沒有完全解決
there is always something new
一直有新的東西在
Of course every complex phenomenon
當然每一個複雜的現象
Of course I want life science now
當然我想現在生命科學
understand this more and more
越來越理解這一點了
This phenomenon occurs in many life sciences
這個在生命科學裡面很多的現象
So it turns out that the simplest phenomenon we understand
所以原來我們理解的最簡單的現象
it has a new law
它都有新的law
new dogma
新的dogma
new principle
新的principle
This is with new rules
這是有new rules
That's why of course
那這個當然也是為什麼
More and more
越來越多的
Those who do physics have to run in
做物理的要跑進去
research life sciences
研究生命科學
because this is new rules
因為這是new rules
new laws
new laws
Then this emerging behavior
那這個emerging behavior
It's not what we imagined
是完全不是我們想像的
The stronger the force
那這個作用力越強
I just talked about scientific issues
那剛才我只講了科學問題
If you think about it, think about human beings
大家想想就想在人類方面
All the problems I just mentioned have arisen
我剛才講的問題都出現了
Our role is also getting stronger
我們的作用也越來越強
The role of people and people in today's world
現在的世界裡面人跟人的作用
And the range distance is getting stronger and stronger
而且的範圍距離也越來越強
Of course it's because of the phone
當然是因為手機的問題
this Internet problem
這個Internet的問題
we can talk to people very far
我們可以跟非常遠的人
Many people act at the same time
非常多的人同時作用
and it's very powerful
而且是非常強的作用
what does long mean
長什麼意思
It's just that you have a lot of leftover information
就是你的資訊殘地非常多
very fast
非常快
information is power
資訊就是作用力
I didn't say it just now
剛才我沒講
In fact, the scope of the cowherd just mentioned
其實剛才講的牛郎範圍
all mean the same thing
都是同樣的意思
The force we are talking about is between the residual information
我們講的作用力就是殘地資訊之間
information interacts with each other
互相殘地資訊就互相作用
These data will generate a large
這些資料就會產生很大的
new human activity
人類的新的活動
There will be many new behaviors appearing
會有很多新的behavior出現
in human society
在人類的社會裡面
This is something we haven't encountered before
這個也是以前我們沒有遇到
Because previous human information
因為以前人類的資訊
are limited to small
都是侷限在小規模裡面
it's different now
現在的不一樣了
completely changed the human
完全改變了人類的
This activity is actually
這個活動其實
So now sociology has become very interesting
所以現在的社會學變得非常 interesting
It is no longer the old sociology
已經不是舊的社會學
Because the emerging behavior may become a
因為對 emerging behavior 可能變成一個
quite important phenomenon
相當重要的現象
thank you all
謝謝大家
ok then thank you very much
好 那我們非常謝謝
Such a brilliant speech by Academician Li
李院士這麼精采的演講
We are now open to ask questions
現在我們開始開放大家提問
The first 10 viewers who asked questions
前面10位提問的觀眾
Chinese medicine hospital is ready
中醫院有準備的
a beautiful gift
精美的禮品一份
for everyone
給大家
so please don't be shy
所以請大家不要客氣
if there is a problem
有問題的話
please raise your hand
請您舉手
so hands can
這樣手可以
The staff can hand over the microphone to everyone
工作人員可以把麥克風交給大家
this one here first
這邊這一位 第一位
The strong force of the teacher
老師那個強作用力
Is the strong force you mentioned related to the injury we usually talk about?
您說的強作用力是否也和我們一般所談論的那個傷是有關聯的
heel injury
跟傷
right
對
Injury is not necessarily related to force
傷不一定是跟作用力有關
But the injury refers to its degree of freedom or its degree of chaos
但傷是講它的這個自由度或者它的混亂的程度
What I just said has something to do with injuries.
剛才講的這些跟傷是有關係
But it's not directly related to force
但這不是直接跟作用力有關係
Strong force does not necessarily mean serious injury
強作用力不一定就大傷
Sometimes the strong force is what you think should be imagined
有時候強作用力反而你覺得應該想像
For example, two cushions are kept together
比如說兩個墊子就被保在一下
can't run around
不能亂跑
So the injury is reduced
所以傷是減少
right
對不對
But if there are many times
但是如果有很多的時候
Not necessarily when it comes out with a new feature
它出來一個新的特點的時候就不一定了
So this has nothing to do with the injury directly.
所以這個跟傷沒有直接的關聯性
I don't know what you just said is also an interesting question
不知道你剛才講的也是很有趣的一個問題
injury related to injury
傷跟傷有關
you know
你知道
With such a strong force, the injury may actually be less
這麼強的作用力 其實傷反而可能變少
Because of yours, some of our little Internet celebrities are very powerful
因為你的 有的我們小的網紅很厲害
How much does an Internet celebrity talk about and how many people it immediately affects
一個網紅講了多少 它馬上影響了多少人
Many people followed it, so it actually hurt less
很多人就跟著它了 所以其實它的傷變少了
ok second place at the end
好 第二位在最後面
Professor Li, I just heard that
李教授 就是我剛剛有聽到就是說
There are electronic teams formed and then there is a coordination mechanism
有形成電子隊 然後還有一個協調機制
tidal conduction
會造成一個類似潮導現象
Tide guide phenomenon, then I would like to ask about this coordination mechanism
潮導現象 那我想問說這個協調機制
It is also seen that when the electronic team is confined to one place
就是也有看到說電子隊在一個 局限在一個地方的時候
It may not be able to form a tidal guide, so is there any way for us to get from this state
它可能也沒辦法形成潮導 那我們有沒有辦法從這個狀態下
use it as a coordinated Is there a way to make a coordinated mechanism
把它用成一個協調的 有沒有辦法製造出一個協調的機制
Then let it return to a tidal state like this
然後讓它又恢復成一個潮導態這樣子
That is how we observe this coordinated phenomenon
那或者是說我們怎麼觀察到這個協調的現象
That's my problem, thanks
那以上是我的問題 謝謝
Of course there are many ways to deal with this phenomenon
對 這個現象當然有很多辦法
I didn't have time to talk about it just now because high tide conduction is complicated.
我剛剛沒時間講 因為高溫潮導很複雜
but it actually
但是它事實上
So this theory is now accepted by most people
所以這個理論是現在大部分人都會接受
I found that a Couper Pair has been formed but there is no guidance
就發覺有Couper Pair已經形成但是沒有操導
Just like the experimental results I showed just now, the results are very certain.
就像我剛才秀的實驗結果就很確定了
It already has a Couper Pair but it doesn't have a coupe
它已經有Couper Pair但是它沒有操導
But how to become a coordination problem is very complicated
但是怎麼變成協調那就很複雜的問題
what you wrote is a good question
你寫的是一個很好的問題
That's what everyone is thinking about
就是大家都在想這個問題
just now I didn't have time to explain
就是剛才我沒有時間解釋
just like dancing
就譬如說剛才跳舞
just use this dance to explain
就用這個跳舞來解釋
For example, at the beginning there is music here
譬如說開始這邊有音樂
some jumping over here
有一些在這邊跳
below there are some over there
下面有一些在那邊
they may not be coordinated
他們兩邊的可能不協調
have been inconsistent
就一直不協調
because he can dance his
因為他可以跳他的
he dances his
他跳他的
But if a multiplayer jump starts in the middle
但是如果中間開始多人跳
When everyone dances together and connects together
大家都跳一起都連在一起的時候
that becomes more and more coordinated
那就會變成越來越協調
Not enough questions don't bump into each other
問題不夠互相不要撞到
push each other up
互相的推起
Then start coordinating
那就開始協調起來了
In fact, this human being has many things
那事實上這個人類有很多事情
For example, if you take a picture, everyone takes random pictures
比如說拍一張每一個人拍都亂拍
When many people shoot together, after a while it becomes very coordinated
很多人一起拍的時候過一陣子就變成非常協調
This is the evidence of many experiments
這個都是有很多實驗的證據
is the coordination
就是這個協調
But in the real material
但是在真正的材料裡面
how do you coordinate
你要怎麼樣做到協調
It's actually quite difficult
其實是滿困難的
It's a matter of directing the coordination
就是操導這個協調的問題
has always been an important issue
一直是一個很重要的問題
But pretty much hasn't been figured out a good way
但是很沒有被找出一個很好的辦法
Then we coordinate when we see coordination
那我們看到協調就協調
uncoordinated uncoordinated
不協調就不協調
But some people will become more coordinated at low temperature
但是有些人在低溫他一定會變成比較協調
Uncoordinated high temperature
高溫比較不協調
It's about business
那這個就跟商有關
it's about business
這就跟商有關
this is another question
這是另外一個問題
ok the gentleman is in the middle
好 那位先生在中間
Hello Yueshi
岳士你好
I just saw you mentioned the experiment you conducted
剛剛中間看到你提到說你們做的實驗
Just watch a VR with a mouse
就老鼠看個VR
Then there is control over him
然後有控制他的
not me doing the experiment
不是我做實驗
That's someone else's experiment
那是人家的實驗
just like China
就中國一樣
We experimented with a professor
我們跟一個教授做實驗
It's a mouse with a little microscope on its head
是老鼠頭上帶了一個小的顯微鏡
in that mini school
放在那個mini school
micro school
micro school
mini micro school
mini micro school
I'm curious
我是好奇說
In the end you concluded that
最後您結論是說
He is also in a critical state
他也是處在一個臨界狀態
Then his parameters
那他肚兩的參數
looks like
看起來是
Other parameters
他肚兩的參數
The parameters of the belly of that picture
那張圖的肚兩的參數
What is the x-axis and y-axis
x軸跟y軸是什麼
Then how to conclude that
然後怎麼樣斷定說
he is in a critical state
他處在一個臨界狀態
I think this is quite interesting
我覺得這個蠻有趣的
here
這裡的
you say
你說
no
不是
Because we're going to put the experimental numbers
因為我們去把實驗的數字
I just didn't have time to talk
我剛剛沒時間講
you asked
你問的
i can talk
我就可以講一下
is the number we put in the experiment
就是我們把實驗的數字
use a model to
用一個模型來
fit it
fit它
In fact, the same as before
其實跟剛才一樣
Anyway, you gave me the experimental data
就是反正你給我實驗數據
I use the simplest model
我用最简单的模型
I want to get the simplest model
我想得到最简单的模型
go fit it
去把它FIT一下
can you fit
能不能FIT
The answer is that it can fit well
答案是可以FIT得很好
Then I can find a model
那我就可以找到一个模型
Then I ask the model now
那我现在问那个模型
if i have model
假如我有模型
I can use it as a physical model
我就可以当作物理的模型来做了
I can put assuming a hypothetical temperature
我可以把假设一个假设的温度
Put the fake temperature in
假的温度放进去
I'll do the math
我来算算看
Various phenomena in this model
这个模型里面的各种现象
then i realize
那我就发觉
how can it have a phase
它怎么会有一个相辨
as if distinguishing
好像相辨那样
Of course it doesn't really look like
当然它没有真的像
Because it's not a big system
因为这个不是很大的系统
For example, we only have 8 or 90
这个比如说我们只有8、90个
Neuroblasts are not millions
神经源不是几百万个
so few systems
所以很少的系统
But at least we see a big
但是至少我们看到一个很大的
This is the PIC
就是这个PIC
that's what we figured out
就是我们算出来的
Its slope is the largest here
它这个斜率在这里是最大
It is also the largest near T.1
也是在T.1的附近最大
so this is weird
所以这个很奇怪
this seems to be a coincidence
这个好像很巧
because there is so much space
因为那么大的空间
it can be found here
它可以在这里
T.1 is the experimental data
T.1是实验的数据
Come in fitting is used to mention
進來fitting是用來提點應
When we extend it
當我們把它擴展以後
We found out why the experimental data is not here
我們發現實驗數據為什麼不在這裡
Why must it be here on the biggest peak
為什麼一定要在最大的峰這裡
Why are you at Dafeng?
為什麼要在大峰那裡
Actually it's not necessary
其實這沒有什麼必要
this is a very strange thing
這個是很奇怪的事情
Of course I'm talking about this
當然這個我講
we're not the first to do it
我們不是第一個做的
What people do is more fine-grained data
人家做的是比較精細的數據
They also found this phenomenon
他們也發覺這個現象
This phenomenon becomes very special
這個現象就變成很特別的
Why do these mouse neurons
為什麼這些老鼠的神經元
From what we see he likes to be on this peak
我們看到的好像他都喜歡在這個峰
In fact, he can be in any
其實他可以在任何
Why does he have to be on this peak
他為什麼一定要在這個峰
Of course this is the most important question
當然這是最重要的問題
Physically speaking
從物理來講
Such a simple model is not very complicated
這麼簡單的模型也不是很複雜
I just said that in fact
剛才講其實裡面
Mostly like the flock of birds
最主要像那個鳥群
looks so complicated
看起來那麼複雜
but they can predict very well
但他們可以predict very well
In fact they can also do dynamic
事實上他們還可以做動態的
prediction of time
時間的prediction
all work
都 work
just can't figure it out
就想不通
Model Actually, I think if you know this
Model其實我想這個如果知道的
Chinese and American professors already know
中美教授已經知道
That is the classical Heisenberg model
那就是classical Heisenberg model
That work can't believe why he works so well
那work簡直是不敢相信他為什麼work這麼好
and things in nature
而自然界的東西
Then why does he work so well
那為什麼他work這麼好
surprise
surprise
the lady
這位女士
Basic This Electron to Thermal Group
基本的這個電子到熱組
And finally to the animal group, the human group
然後最後到動物組 人組
Then we often use
那麼之間我們常常用
you from the couple effect
你從couple effect
to this highest this
到這個最高的這個
The collective behavior you are talking about
你現在講的集體的行為
There are some in the middle called Cui Xing
那中間有一些叫做萃形
also steady state
也好steady state
Can you use a very simple sentence between this
這個之間你能不能用一個很簡單的話
string it on force
把它串起來在作用力上
From a point of view of force
從作用力的一個觀點來
Look at such a collective behavior
看這樣的一個集體的行為
forget about it
不想了
The force must be present to have a non-transition
作用力是一定要有才会有非 transition
Without force, of course there won't be
没有作用力当然不会有
That non transition from one boundary to another
那非 transition 从一个界限变另外一个界限
Actually nothing has changed, right?
其实东西没变 对吧 水
A water molecule is a water molecule, a gas
水分子就水分子 本来是气体
Become liquid again, become solid again, become ice again
又变成液体 又变成固体 变成冰
The thing has not changed, the composition has not changed, but its shape can change
东西没有变 组成没变 但它的形态可以变
Did the force change or did not change
作用力有没有变 也没有变
In principle you can write down a force
In principle 你可以写下一个作用力
Especially with the current calculation method, you can calculate
尤其现在的计算方法 你可以算出来
But here, of course, is what I just said
可是在这里面当然就是刚才讲的
This is a question of statistical body thermodynamics
这个是统计体员热力学的问题
Because the exchange of injury and energy changes the harmony of each other
因为伤跟能量的交换 改变互相的调和
you can come out in different shapes
你可以出来不同的形状
Of course now I know this
当然现在知道这个情况
That is the simplest case more complicated
那个是最简单的情况 更复杂
many complex traps
很多复杂的陷阱
Like I didn't have time to talk just now
像剛才我沒時間講
Our model is actually related to last year's Nobel Prize
我們這個模型其實是跟去年諾貝爾獎有關的
This is called the Spin Glass Model.
這個是叫做Spin Glass Model 智旋玻璃模型
with last year's nobel prize winner
跟去年諾貝爾獎得主
I spoke two or three years late
我晚講了兩三年
two nobel laureates
就是兩個諾貝爾獎得主
Everything I do is related to this
做的東西都跟這有關
This is Zhixuan Glass Model
這個是智旋不Glass Model
that's... that's more complicated
那就是...那就比較複雜
Then it is often said here that there is no...
那這裡常常講就沒有...
that is not to say
就是說不是說
You said that even a force can be negative energy
你講一個作用力都可以負能
That's what I've been wanting to...
就是我剛才一直要...
The emphasis is that the system is different
emphasize就是系統不一樣
The force is different
作用力不一樣
ingredients if different
成分如果不一樣
You may have many new phenomena
你可能就有很多新的現象
not what you thought
不是你原來想像的
Especially when the force is stronger
尤其作用力越強的時候
more complexity
複雜性越多
we already know this
這一點我們已經知道了
more and more clear
越來越清楚了
It has more new behaviors that you can't imagine will come out
它有更多你想像不到的新的behavior會出來
This phenomenon is more and more
這個在物裡越來越多的現象
But I think in the life sciences
但是我覺得在生命科學
It's been happening for a long time
老早就有這個現象
I have had this for a long time
老早就有這種
existing problems
存在的問題
because of the life sciences
因為生命科學裡面
In fact, I think it's all strongly correlated.
其實我覺得都是強關聯作用
It's all a powerful system at work
都是很強的系統在作用
So it actually has a large
所以它其實有很大的
Many emerging phenomena
很多的emerging的現象
I still don't understand
都往上還不理解
But that's the direction of research
不過就是研究的方向了
But this is no universal theory
但是這個是沒有什麼universal theory
This is actually to tell you that
這個其實要告訴你就是
No Z theory
沒有Z theory
good lady in the back
好那位後面的女士
Hello Mr. Li
李老師您好
It's the picture on the left
就是那個左邊那張圖
It's actually quite interesting
其實是蠻有趣的
So my question is
所以我的問題是
Here with the whole population
這裡跟整個population
Nuron's threshold
Nuron 的threshold
does it matter
有關係嗎
Because Nuron's firing exceeds the threshold
因為Nuron的firing過threshold
Is it 0101?
是0101嗎
That is we made a simplification
那是我們做了一個簡化
The easiest thing for a physical person to do
物理人做最簡單
When you see a cow, turn it into a ball
看到一隻牛就把它變成圓球
leave it alone
就不要去管它了
But the same thing happened to us
但同樣的我們馬了靈異
Of course what we do is in our Poverty Paper
當然我們做的在我們的Poverty Paper裡面
Is to use different Threshold to show
是用不同的Threshold都去秀
no relevance
沒有關聯性
at least within reason
至少在合理的範圍之內
there is no correlation
上是沒有什麼關聯性
Thanks
謝謝
THIS ANSWER IS FULL AND VERY ROBUS
這個答案是還滿非常ROBUS
This is what we most want to amplify in Paper
這一點也是我們在Paper最想amplify
very strange
很奇怪
Why so ROBUS
為什麼這麼ROBUS
This is also a strange thing
這個也是一個奇怪的事情
lady in front
前面的女士
Thank you teacher for sharing
謝謝老師分享
I have a question
我有一個問題
I'm sorry, I'm not learning at all
對不起我不是學完全不懂
But in terms of deepening
但是是深化方面
You mentioned that when you danced just now
你這邊提到剛剛你跳舞的時候
There are times when there is not much pairing
有不太有成對的時候
Then I also talk about it in class
那我自己上課也講說
When there are encounters with some electronic teams that are not paired
當有碰到一些有電子隊沒有成對
he will rob others
他會去搶別人
We electron orbital group two two electrons
我們電子軌道組兩個兩個電子
Of course when they rob
那當然他們搶的時候
Grab him and release him to become Free Radicals
搶到他釋放出來變成Free Radicals
like say
像比方說
The leaves of the tooth iron become iron nuggets
牙鐵的叶子變成鐵粒
So iron becomes Free Radical
所以鐵變成Free Radical
It can't be a pair
它沒有辦法成為Pair
It will do Chain Reaction
它就去做Chain Reaction
Damage caused by grinding
造成包磨的Damage
and then finally cause some
然後最後造成一些
Mutual or casino tool issues
互相的或是Casino具的問題
But when you talk about it
可是在你這個地方講到說
Squeeze it out into a UFO attitude
把它擠出來變成UFO的態度
seems positive
好像是正向的
These two are a bit
這兩個有點
Very special and comparative explanation
很特別有比較的解釋
The UFO is not where it becomes Free Radical
UFO的地方不是它變成Free Radical
in fact limit it
事實上是把它限制住
only put that
只有把那個
I just didn't have time to talk
我剛剛沒時間講
Inside Vortex
在Vortex裡面
Is there any paired electrons
是有沒有成對的電子
it won't be paired
它不會成對
Each has its own electricity inside
都有單獨的電在裡面
so it puts all those extra pairs of electrons in there
所以它就把那些多成對的電子都放在那裡
The key is like that
關鍵牢那樣子
then don't run around
那你不要亂跑
just mess with others
就搗亂別人
how smart do you see
你看多聰明
Your Radical
你的Radical
if you make it this far
如果你們做到到這裡
you can cure
你們就可以治藥了
right
對不對
Radical
Radical
don't let it run around
不要給它亂跑
and instead of us putting it in
而且不是我們放進去
We rot it becomes a result of nature
我們爛它變成是自然界產生的結果
it will rot automatically
自動會爛它
don't run around
不要亂跑
Why
為什麼
because it runs around
因為它亂跑
The resulting energy will increase and destroy the entire tire
造成的能量會增加,會破壞整個胎
The whole tire is so big, so it will be limited to a certain place
整個胎那麼大,所以會把它限制在某一個地方
So radical can't rap
所以radical不能rap跑
But in life science, it will come out to do chain reaction
可是在life science它裡面就會跑出來做chain reaction
Yes, it won't run out, so there are certain ways to deal with this problem on its side
對,它不會跑出來,所以它這邊都有一定的辦法處理這個問題
So it automatically solves it without this
所以它自動的解出來就會沒有這個
This is of course Apricotium nano, don't talk about the important place
這個當然是Apricotium nano,不要講的重要的地方
This is automatic, this nature will automatically give you a solution
這個自動的,這個自然界就自動給你一個解
It is this electronic tire that automatically gives you a solution, which solves this problem
就是這個電子胎自動給你一個解,就解決了這個問題
And the solution is very beautiful, very beautiful solution to this problem
而且解決非常漂亮,非常漂亮的解決這個問題
No human intervention is required at all
完全沒有需要人工的加入
It tells you that what we now prove is the solution of the natural state
它就告訴你,我們現在證明是自然態的解而已
So it's not that we invent new solutions, it doesn't, it's just that after it's poured out
所以不是說我們發明新的解,它不是,它只是它倒出來之後
We can fully explain this solution
我們完全可以解釋這個解
Then this solution will tell you in the experiment
那這解本來實驗就告訴你
Life science has a chain reaction, which is negative
Life science has a chain reaction,是負面的
Life science has a...
Life science has a...
It has no pre-reaction because it cannot come out
它沒有前reaction,因為它不能出來
it's confined inside, it can't come out
它被限制在裡面,它不能出來
this is a very special place
這個就是很特別的地方
This is what Mr. Murray just said
這個是剛才梅瑞先生講的這個
your question is very good
你講的問題很好
But there is an automatic way
但是有自動的辦法
I think the human body can do it automatically.
我想人體搞不好也有自動辦法
How to control Ratical
怎麼控制Ratical
we have three here
我們這邊有三位
We are behind first, and then the second is here
我們後面先,然後第二位在這邊
Thank you academician for your speech
謝謝院士的演講
Then I have a few questions I want to ask the academician
那我有幾個小問題想要請教院士
The first one is whether all substances
第一個,就是是不是所有的物質
There will be critical phenomena
都會有臨界的現象
Either the temperature is too high or the temperature is too low
只不過是溫度太高或溫度太低
It's just a matter of whether I can measure it or I can't measure it
我量得到或我量不到的問題而已
The second little problem is
那第二個小問題是
Because you just mentioned the collective behavior of humans
因為你剛剛有提到人類的集體行為
seems to be related to what you just mentioned
似乎跟你剛剛所提到的
Clustering may be somewhat conceptual
群聚現象可能有一些觀念性
Then my question is to ask
那我的問題是問說
Let things like war, plague, or famine
讓戰爭、瘟疫或是饑荒這些事情
Is that also a so-called critical phenomenon?
那是不是也是所謂的臨界現象
The third question is to ask
那第三個問題是想要問說
Is that as long as a certain amount is reached?
那是不是只要到達某一個數量
That means there is only one bird today that we may not see
也就是說今天只有一隻鳥可能我們看不到
That might be ten birds and I might not even see them
那可能十隻鳥我可能也看不到
But if I accumulate ten thousand birds
可是我如果累積了一萬隻鳥的話
can i see this
我是不是就可以看到這樣
such a group phenomenon
這樣的一個群體現象
It's like the war just now or the plague or the famine
那如同剛剛的戰爭或是瘟疫或是饑荒
Is it that these events will eventually happen in the history of mankind?
那是不是這些事件終究會在人類的歷史上發生
It's just that the amount we accumulate
只不過我們累積的數量
Or a certain amount of accumulation has not been reached
或是累積的某個量沒有到達
So it just happens early or it happens late
所以它只是提早發生或是延遲發生
Thanks
謝謝
This question is the hardest to answer
這個問題是最難回答的
This question is very interesting
這個問題是很有趣的問題
not this question is a very good question
不是這個問題是非常好的問題
questions we've been thinking about
我們一直在想的問題
but it's hard to answer
但是很難回答
Because my problem is that our analysis now
因為我的問題是我們現在的分析
Our previous analysis method is different
我們以前分析的方法不太一樣
we don't have enough data
我們的數據不夠
Your problem now is with this data
你現在的問題就是跟這個數據
if we do physics
我們做物理的話
That is to say, I don't like to think about philosophical problems casually.
就是說我不太喜歡隨便去想哲學的問題
Then we become philosophers
那我們就變哲學家了
Physicist is what I want to see the data
物理學家就是我要看到數據
what kind of data
那為什麼樣的數據
I can analyze it like this
是我能夠這樣子去分析
Is this the zero line?
這個是不是零界線
Is your war border zero
你的戰爭是不是零界線
that might not be like
那個可能不太像
because of aggressiveness
因為侵略性
like i think everyone
好像我覺得每一個人
our DNA may have
我們的DNA可能就有了
It's a bit troublesome now
這個時候已經有點麻煩
this is i'm not sure yet
這個是我還不確定
It's a phenomenon of how many groups
這是有多少是群體的現象
Or he already had this idea
或者是他個人已經有的這個想
That’s what I said group is different from Emerging
就是我講群體跟Emerging是不一樣的
group is a phenomenon
群體是有一些現象
But he is not necessarily Emerging's Behavior
但他不一定是Emerging的Behavior
OK, as long as he already has
OK,就他本來就有的
Say you train the army
比如說你訓練軍隊
Everyone shoots and hits, right?
每個人都會開槍會打人對不對
He trains well by himself
他一個人都訓練好
that gathers them
那把他們集結
they also do the same thing
他們還做一樣的事情
He has no Emerging behavior
他沒有什麼Emerging behavior
His Behavior is the original
他的Behavior就是原來
each individual
每一個的個別的
and then just get together
然後只聚在一起而已
it's two different things
這是兩回事
What I just said is that it has a completely new phenomenon
我剛才講的這個是它完全有新的現象
Like the superconducting invention just now, two batteries
像剛才超導明來兩個電池
should be mutually exclusive
應該是互相排斥的
it does not exclude
它不排斥
Actually I didn't have time to talk just now
事實上我剛才沒時間講
its just the battery and
它剛才的電池以及
A battery in the superconducting state is not the original battery
在超導態的電池不是原來的電池
You know that batteries and superconductivity are two different things
你原來瞭解電池跟超導態是兩回事
this is totally different
這個是完全不一樣的
this is completely new
這是完全新的
If you use the old concept, you're screwed
你如果用舊的觀全想就完蛋了
So I kept talking about new phenomena
所以我後來一直講新的現象
New Law new this understanding
新的Law新的這個understanding
not the old way
不是舊的方法
This point is that physics has begun to understand
這一點是物理已經開始比較理解了
I think some subjects
我是覺得有些學科
Still think it comes from reductionism
還是覺得它從reductionism
can solve everything
就可以解決everything
I think of course it is a bit difficult
我覺得當然是有點difficult
There are many problems with reductionism
有很多問題是reductionism
May be no way to use
可能是沒有辦法用的
You can't use the reduction method
你就不能用reduction的方法
use each individual
用每一個個體
I know the genes now
現在的基因我已經知道了
strong association, your genome
強關聯作用,你的基因體
Although I know all the genes are sorted
雖然我知道所有的基因排序
It's not necessarily impossible to understand genetics
也不見得沒辦法對基因的理解
because they are really strongly correlated
因為他們是真的強關聯作用
it has many new phenomena
它有很多新的現象
It's not us, you used to know everyone
不是我們,你原來知道每一個就知道的
I think we understand this too
這個我想我們也了解了
But it's not unusual in physics
但在物理講這不稀奇
so we've seen too much of this
所以我們已經看到太多這樣的事情
It's not as simple as you thought
它不是你原來想像這麼簡單
very strong
作用力很強
but i answered your question
但我是回答了你一個問題
Because I don't remember any other questions from you.
因為你其他問題我都不記得
How many birds do you want
你說要多少鳥上
That's also good question
That's also good question
Same problem as coherence just now
跟剛才的coherence同樣的問題
How much is the answer I don't know
要多少答案是我不知道
You have seen it with very little
你擺得很少就已經看
As I said just now, I only used seventy or eighty neurons
像我剛才有講我只用了七八十個neuron
I can already see that it looks like a cretial state
我就已經看出來很像cretial state
But I dare not say it is in the cretial state
但我不敢講它是在cretial state
because it is not infinity
因為它不是infinity
But its behavior has already begun to appear
但是它的behavior就已經開始有出現了
But from the mathematical definition
但是从数学定义
you can't be so rigid by definition
你不能定义得那么rigorous
but physically
但是从物理上讲
it behaves like
它 behavior 很像
already too close
已经太接近
already makes me a little uneasy
已经令我有点不安了
Actually I see it turns out to be unsettling
其实我看它结果是不安的
I don't know why there is such a result
我不曉得为什么会有这样的结果
then we thought we were doing it wrong
那我们以为我们做错了
So we've been researching
所以我们一直研究
Now with more data
现在有数据更多了
It's an uneducated number that gives us more data
它这个无教数给我们更多数据
the answer is the same
答案都是一样
This is of course very strange
这点当然很奇怪
very interesting question
非常有趣的问题
But this I don't know
但这个我也不曉得会
don't need a lot
不需要很多
OK
OK
But it takes a lot to change infinity
但要变 infinity 要很多
Otherwise you can't see infinity
要不然你看不到 infinity
Okay, thank you
好 谢谢
Just this one
刚刚这位
in the middle
在中间
please raise your hand
请举一下手
I can get you the microphone
可以拿麦克风给你
good
好
Hello, Li Yuanshi
好 李渊士你好
just now i mentioned
刚刚我提到
There will be a special coherence between Cooprope
Cooprope之间会有同调性这个特殊
i want to ask
我想请问
synchronous coordination
在产生同步协调
Is this phenomenon immediate or is it a gradual behavior
這個現象是屬於立即性還是是一個漸進的行為
The BCX theory is immediacy
在bcx理論是立即性
so its resistance becomes 0
所以它電阻變0
No resistance to 0 without peers
沒有同僚就不會電阻到0
As soon as it reaches below tc the resistance is 0
它一到tc以下電阻就是0
Not 0.001
不是0.001哦
It's not 0.001 either
也不是0.001哦
it is 0
它就是0哦
OK
OK
no resistance
就沒有電阻
So the question you just mentioned is that the experimental data is Mangeli
所以這個你剛才講的問題是實驗的數據是Mangeli
But high temperature superconductivity is different.
但是高溫超導可不一樣哦
The high-temperature superconductivity mentioned just now is a bit embarrassing.
剛才講的高溫超導就有點崔起了
Companionship and pairing are two different temperatures
同僚性跟配對是兩個不同的溫度
look first
先看看
OK
OK
Then this is a different temperature
那這個就是不一樣的溫度
Pair first, then tune
先是配對再同調
But thinking about it now so it's more negative
但是現在想想所以它更負面
you can tell it's uneven
你可以看出來它不均勻
its the same strip , its this dancing room
它的同條,它的這個跳舞的房間
Not one hall, many small halls, many highlands, different
不是一個大廳,很多小廳,很多高地,要不同的
different place
不一樣的地方
Everybody's dancing over there, as you can imagine
大家在那邊跳舞,你可以想像
If there is such a scene, this dance must be very exciting
如果有這樣子的場面,這個跳起來一定很精彩
How can I dance without being strong or...
怎麼跳的又不壯到又不...
that's complicated
那很複雜
Then this, you can imagine, that is like Gao Wenchao brain
那這個,就可以想像,那個就是像高文超腦
a bit complicated
有點複雜性
more challenges
更多的挑戰
But it doesn't have to be the same
但是它不是一定是同條
It's just a pair
就是配對就同條
So it, but the theory of BCS is that pairing is the same
所以它,可是BCS的理論是配對就同條
ok here miss here
好,這邊小姐在這裡
Hello teacher, I don't know if there is...
老師好,不知道有...
Is there any chance to listen to the teacher's introduction
有沒有機會可以聽老師介紹
The video that just didn't have time to play
剛剛沒有來得及播放的那個影片
Thanks
謝謝
Is that... blessed?
那個... 持福的是不是
that...
那個...
how to go back
要怎麼回去
that...that will...
那個...那個會...
The one I put...
我放的那個...
it's here
在這裡
OK here
這裡 OK
Like this time he put a...
像這個時候他把一個...
liquid hazard
液態害
That thing just now was a liquid hazard
剛才那個東西是一個液態害
put that superconductor in
放那個超導體放進去
put liquid harm
放液態害
Then he put a magnet on it
然後他就把一個磁鐵放在上面
Look at him now...
你看他現在在...
he wants to push him
他想要推他
he can push
他可以推動
no middle...
沒有中間...
I wanted to do an experiment for you guys
我本來想做實驗給你們
but...
但是...
I guess the experiment didn't see clearly
我想實驗還沒看得清楚
it shines more clearly
它這個照得更清楚
it pushes it
它推動它
it didn't touch
它沒有碰到
That magnet is floating
那個磁鐵是在懸空的
real suspension
真正的懸空
look at its invisible hands
你看它無形的手
yes catch this
是把這個抓住
but it's not tight enough now
但它現在不夠緊
so it pushes it down a little bit
所以它把它按下去一點
The magnetic field lines go in and exceed how many
那磁力線更進去超到幾
Then it can be lifted
然後它就可以提起來
You see such a heavy whole block
你看那麼重的一個整整塊
Magnets can pull it up
磁鐵就可以把它拉起來
then it is here
那它這裡就是
put this in too
把這個也放進去
take this
把這個
It's actually right here in the glove
它其實這裡在手套是對的
That temperature is what I just said
那個溫度是剛才我講
liquid hi is -200 degrees
液態嗨是-200度
It's minus 200 degrees
是零下200度
so around 200 degrees
所以200度左右
It must wear gloves
它這個一定要戴手套
Otherwise it will show here
要不然它這裡就秀
It puts an orange on top
它擺一個擺一支橘子在上面
it doesn't matter
也沒有關係
still heavy enough
還是夠重
Then here it will show
那這裡它就要秀是
it does something special
它做了一個特別的東西
it's magnetic
它這個磁
its vertical line is uneven
它立線是不均勻的
The inside is different from the outside
裡面跟外面是不一樣大
I want to say that once the lines of magnetic force have a curvature
想說一旦磁力線有一個彎度
it takes this
它就把這個
Wait a minute and it will put this
等一下它就會把這個
put it on
放上去
you see
你看到
it won't stop
它不會停喔
such a little effort
這麼一點點力氣
push it a little
把它稍微推一下
it keeps spinning on this
它就在這個上面一直轉喔
can turn for a long time
可以轉很久很久
it can spin for a long time
它可以轉很久很久
I'm running out of time to show
剛剛我就要沒時間秀
this is just for show
這個只是給你秀
it this
它這個
as long as the position is right
只要這個位置對了
it can go all the way
它可以一直轉
because it has no resistance
因為它沒有阻力
It has a little Energy cost
它有一點點Energy cost
very low is this
非常低的是這個
When the lines of magnetic force enter and exit
這個磁力線進出的時候
a little bit
有一點點
it has very little energy
它能量非常小
to it as a whole
對它整個來講
so it lasts a long time
所以它可以用很久
I just said that the real experiment is not like this
我剛才講真正的實驗不是這樣
Seriously, take a superconductor and make a coil
說真拿超導體做成一個線圈
Make one, then connect and add battery
做一個 然後有通了加了電池
The superconducting current starts running and the battery is removed
超導電流開始跑 然後把電池拿走
The current can run here for several years
電流在這裡可以跑幾年
It still has energy cost
當中它還是有能量的cost
Why? There is radiation
為什麼? 有 radiation
but that's too little
但是那個太少了
Not important to the whole energy
對整個能量來講是不重要
so it can be years
所以它可以到幾年
Then they shut down the experiment
後來他們就關掉這個實驗
because there's no need to do it
因為沒必要做下去
It means that the resistance is 0
就表示這個電阻是0
In fact, what they want to show is
其實他們要秀的就是
Otherwise, no one would believe
要不然也沒有人相信說
Is the resistance really 0?
電阻真的0嗎?
Is it 10-------16 times
是不是10的-------16 次發
10 of -------- 25 times issued
10的--------25 次發
But we now what I just told you
但是我們現在我剛才跟你講的
Actually the proof is that it is true 0
其實這證據是它是真的0
So it is a quantum number
所以是一個quantum number
0 is not an hour
不是一個時數的0
is a real discreet quantum number
是一個真正的discreet quantum number
0,1,2,3, that is 0
0,1,2,3,那就是0
when later many
當到後來很多
Physics is about finding the first, second, and third of the frame and pillow, which Nanova said
物理講是找到框枕第一、二、三這些Nanova講的
It is this system that has a certain value
就是這個系統它有一定的數值
This 1 is not 1.001 0.999
這個1也不是1.001 0.999
Even a DG can't be wrong
就是一個DG都不能錯的
this is quantum
這個是量子
This is the macroscopic quantum
這是巨觀量子
Macroscopic quantum like this
像這個就巨觀量子
such a big thing
這麼大一個東西
all behave
都behave
This is the macroscopic quantum
這是巨觀量子
Of course we want to find this at room temperature
當然我們希望在室溫找到這個
Then there's the real room-temperature quantum attitude
那就有真正的室溫的量子態度
Now since the first superconductor is 4 degrees
現在因為第一個超導體是4度
absolute temperature 4 degrees
絕對溫度4度
How high is it now?
現在最高已經到多少度了
High temperature superconductors can be pressurized up to 165 degrees
高溫超導體最高是加了壓是165度
Negative pressure is 135 degrees
負加壓是135度
But recently a new superconductor has been learned
但是最近有學新的超導體是在
Very high pressure is tight with sea seat
非常大的壓是用海座緊的
Kangkang, that Haocheng came to Shiwen, but this has not been officially accepted
康康,那浩城是到世文,但是這個都沒有被正式的接受了
This one still has Zeng Na, and Zeng Chao
這個還有曾拿,還有在曾炒
But in any case, there is hope, there is no reason why it cannot be higher
但是不管怎麼講,有希望,沒有什麼理由說不能更高了
Maybe you don’t need Shiwen, if there is a guide to do it in the icy and snowy winter
也許不用世文,如果在很冬天這種冰天雪地的時候,有可以操導可以做
Yes, during this suddenly everyone thought, if you look at this and think why
對,這個當中突然大家想,如果你看著這就想著為什麼
At that time, everyone was a sensation, and they went to the meeting in the middle of the night
那時候大家轟動了,三更半夜還去開會
Thousands of people, not a few meetings
幾千個人,不是很少的會議一聽
More than 2,000 people were crowded inside
兩千多個人都擠在裡面了
I have no place to go in, I stand at the farthest place to watch
我都進去沒地方,站在最遠的地方看
Everyone uploaded the slideshow in five minutes, and posted what I did and what I did
那個投影片每個人五分鐘上去,傳了我做了什麼,我涼了什麼
Then this, but why this?
那這個,可是這個為什麼呢?
Because when you look at this, you think about the issue of energy, which is too much related to this
因為你看著這就想能源的問題,跟這個是太大的關聯性
With this can solve a big energy problem
有了這個可以解決很大的能源問題
but luckily we haven't done it yet
但是我們很幸運的還沒做成功
still working hard
還在努力之中
ok we have no problem
好 我們已經沒有問題了
I just heard Li Benshi answer so many questions
剛剛聽李便世回答了這麼多問題
such a wonderful speech
這麼精彩的演講
Let's applaud again, thank you Li Bianshi
讓我們再次掌聲謝謝李便世
I would like to thank you all for coming here
在這邊要再謝謝大家來參加
Feast of knowledge tonight
今天晚上的知識饗宴
Tell you about our next lecture
跟大家報告一下我們下一次的講座
It will be on the evening of Tuesday, December 13th
會在12月13號 禮拜二的晚上
it's seven o'clock
也是七點鐘
We've come to a completely different topic
我們到了一個完全不一樣的講題
The topic is the encounter between history and criminology
題目是歷史學與犯罪學的相遇
What I want to talk about is the analysis of the theft crime in the middle of the 19th century
要講的是19世紀中業竊盜犯罪的分析
So the speaker is researcher Wurenshu
所以主講人是烏人樹研究員
Is a researcher at the Institute of Modern History of Zhongan Academy of Sciences
是中安就院近代史研究所的研究員
So the same in
所以同樣的在
in this venue
在這一個場地
Please if you are interested
請大家如果有興趣的話
You can register online
可以上網報名
thank you all
謝謝大家
have a nice evening everyone
祝大家有一個愉快的夜晚
Thank you Li Yan
謝謝李燕飾